<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief, and plain apology written by John Wheelwright: wherein he doth vindicate himself, from al [sic] those errors, heresies, and flagitious crimes, layed to his charge by Mr. Thomas Weld, in his short story, and further fastened upon him, by Mr. Samuel Rutherford in his survey of antinomianisme. Wherein free grace is maintained in three propositions, and four thesis [sic] ...</title>
            <author>Wheelwright, John, 1594-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186427</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52529092</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52529092</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179239</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06542)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2781:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief, and plain apology written by John Wheelwright: wherein he doth vindicate himself, from al [sic] those errors, heresies, and flagitious crimes, layed to his charge by Mr. Thomas Weld, in his short story, and further fastened upon him, by Mr. Samuel Rutherford in his survey of antinomianisme. Wherein free grace is maintained in three propositions, and four thesis [sic] ...</title>
                  <author>Wheelwright, John, 1594-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 [i.e. 27], [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Cole, printer and book-seller, at the sign of the printing-press in Cornhill, near the Royal Exchang,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Short story by Thomas Weld referred to in title sometimes attributed to John Winthrop.</note>
                  <note>P. 22 missing in number only.</note>
                  <note>[5] pages at end contain catalog of books printed by Peter Cole, and errata.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Weld, Thomas, 1590?-1662.</term>
               <term>Winthrop, John, 1588-1649.</term>
               <term>Rutherford, Samuel, 1600?-1661. --  Survey of the spirituall antichrist.</term>
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antinomianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179239:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179239:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief, and PLAIN APOLOGY Written By JOHN WHEELWRIGHT: Wherein he doth vindicate himſelf, From al thoſe <hi>Errors, Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>Flagitious Crimes,</hi> layed to his charge by Mr. <hi>Thomas Weld,</hi> in his ſhort ſtory, And further Faſtened upon him, by Mr. <hi>Samuel Rutherford</hi> in his Survey of Antinomianiſme. Wherein Free Grace is Maintained in three Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Four Theſis VIZ.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prop. 1.</hi> That the Faith of Gods Elect, whereby they do believe on Chriſt, is not grounded upon a conditional Promiſe, made to gracious qualifications previous to Faith.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prop. 2.</hi> That the firſt evidence of our Juſtification, is not any work of Sanctification.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prop. 3.</hi> That an act of Faith, which is grounded upon gracious Qualifications, previous to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and Works as firſt evidences, is legal.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Theſ. 1.</hi> That Aſſurance of Juſtfication from Works of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is not our Aſſurance of Faith.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Theſ. 2.</hi> That Juſtification goes in order before our Beleeving.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Theſ. 3.</hi> That the Faith of Gods Elect, whereby they do beleeve on Chriſt, is grounded upon a free, ſimple, abſolute promiſe of Grace.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Theſ. 4.</hi> That all Promiſes proper and peculiar to the Goſpel, are abſolute.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own cauſe ſeemeth juſt: but his neighbor commeth, and Searcheth him,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The path of the juſt is as the ſhining light, that ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 4.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward Cole,</hi> Printer and Book-ſeller, at the Sign of the Printing-Preſs in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchang. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179239:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>IF that old Maxime of <hi>Jeroms</hi> be true; <hi>In ſuſpicione haereſeas nolo quanquam eſſe patientem,</hi> ſurely there is no reaſon, I ſhould ſuffer what is written againſt me, by Mr. <hi>Thomas Weld,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Samuel Rutherford,</hi> without any reply. The <hi>Montaniſts, Priſcilianiſts, Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ticks, Borboritae, Caenoſy,</hi> that dirty ſect, <hi>Thomas Munſterus, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>annes Leidenſis, Kniperdolingus,</hi> have not many more marks of infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and reproach drawn upon them, then theſe my adverſaries have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed upon me. They bring me upon the Stage, preſent me unto the worlds view, Stigmatize me, for an Arch-Familiſt, Antinomian, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertine, ſeducer: lay me under the guilt of Contempt of Authority, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edition: relate me to an hundred, and eleven errors, nine unſavoury ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, make al the hereſies, and enormous crimes in the Country to center <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e. My conſcience doth acquit me with ſuch cleer evidence, againſt al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſe horrible accuſations, that I could willingly paſs by al in ſilence, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not true which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith; <hi>qui fidens conſcientiae ſuae negligit fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m ſuam crudelis eſt.</hi> I am no ſtoick, but very ſenſible of al indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s, and injuries put upon me: yet ſhould I not in this caſe, have opened <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mouth, did not the Loud, and ſtrong cal of Mr. <hi>Weld,</hi> and Mr. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utherford,</hi> conſtrain me to publiſh my Defence. Should I conſent by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ful ſilence, to what they charge upon me, not only to the great diſhonor of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelf, Miniſtry, and my relations here upon earth, but of my Lord, and Maſter, in heaven Chriſt Jeſus, I ſhould grievouſly ſin, againſt the Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, Nature and Grace.</p>
            <p>The beſt way to cleere up things is to follow that rule of <hi>Ariſtotles,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The truth I not only evidence it ſelf, but diſcover falſhod. <hi>Veniat veritas ut poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falſitas de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ehendi.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Wheelwright,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179239:2"/>
            <head>Free Grace maintained, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE chief Cauſe of all my ſufferings in <hi>New England</hi> (ſo far as I know) was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Doctrine, with its Application, which I delivered in the Church of <hi>Boſton,</hi> concerning the grounds of a ſpecial Faith, the ſubſtance whereof is contained in theſe three following Propoſitions, which I ſhall confirm.</p>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>PROPOSITION I.</hi> That the Faith of Gods Elect, whereby they do believe on Chriſt, is not grounded upon a conditional Promiſe, made to gracious qualifications previous to Faith.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, There are no ſuch gracious qualifications precedent to union; for then ſhould that which is born of the fleſh be Spirit, a man dead in treſpaſſes, and ſins, put forth acts of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al life, an evil tree bring forth good fruit, an enemy to God do his Will, a perſon without union do ſomething, he muſt act graciouſly who hath no formal principles of ſuch acts, then may a man pleaſe God without Faith, and qualifie himſelf by ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſetting up of antecedent gracious qualifications, as a ground of our Faith, is quiet oppoſite to the clear revelation of Gods free grace, and the miniſtration of his power in our converſion, and the Lord walks in a contrary way towards his Elect. He cryes down all fleſh, all power in our ſelves to act graciouſly, that the glory of his power may be revealed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. He puts out the light of ſeeming gracious qualifications, and cals us out of darkneſs, making us ſenſible of the palpable darkneſs of ſin, and miſery, wherein we are inthraled, that the light of his grace, and mercy in Chriſt, may appear unto us, (as it is in it ſelf) marvellous, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. The almighty power of God, the marvellous grace, and mercy of God towards us in Chriſt, could never be ſo apprehended of us in our effectual call, did we look at our ſelves as precedently gracious.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They who ground their Faith upon theſe gracious qualifications can never be at any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty. By what light do ſuch (being in the ſtate of nature) diſcern that they are rightly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, having performed (as they call it) the Condition of Faith? It is not the light of the Spirit, Faith, and Word.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They who are of this judgement, build their Faith upon an imaginary foundation, a Work, and a Word: The Work is done out of Chriſt, the Word is a ſuppoſed promiſe made to this Work, unto which the free promiſe of Grace hath no reſpect.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>The Lord invites ſuch as thirſt, and are gracciouſly qualified to come unto him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If it be meant of Evangelical thirſting, it preſuppoſeth union, and a formall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of life, dead men thirſt-not. They are not called upon firſtly to believe, but to renew Faiths act: Neither is it their grace, but their want of grace, which is uſed as an Argument to perſwade them to come.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>By gracious qualifications, and preparations for Chriſt, is not meant qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons formally gracious, but only ſuch as effect, or have relation to true Grace, which doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily follow them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:179239:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is acknowledged that ſome Writers thus expreſs themſelves; They raiſe up theſe qualifications to a very great height, and aſſert that they are proper to Gods Elect, not to be found in any reprobate, calling them the Condition of Faith, and that the Soul thus prepared ſees that the promiſe belongs unto her; yet deny that they are works of Sanctification. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee but they who affirm that they are works diſtinguiſhing between Elect, and Reprobates, and Arguments that the promiſe belongs unto them, and yet will not have them to flow from a formal principle of ſaving Grace, do imply a contradiction; Whether theſe qualifications, and preparations for Chriſt, be denominated gracious, formally, efficiently, or relatively in order to true Grace, it cannot be ſhewed out of Gods Word, That any promiſe runs thus; If you be thus, or thus prepared for Chriſt, then he belongs unto you: ye have performed the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the benefit conditioned is yours: I do acknowledge that the formal object of an efficacious Call are Elect perſons prepared by the Law, being ſick, loſt, dead ſinners to their own apprehenſions, to the end that ſin may abound, and grace abound, and that to their ſenſe, and feeling, <hi>Rom</hi> 5.20. But there ate no preparations wrought either by Law, or Goſpel which ſo qualifie the Soul, as a man may conclude from thence, That God cals with a purpoſe to ſave.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Culverwel</hi> in his Treatiſe of Faith, much bewailes the cordition of ſuch, who build their Faith upon the change of their lives, affirming, That they can never have ſound, and ſtedfaſt Faith, but an unconſtant, and ſtaggering opinion at the beſt.</p>
               <p>This grounding of Faith upon gracious qualifications before union, is much oppugned by Mr. <hi>Coltan</hi> in his <hi>New Covenant,</hi> and by Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> in his <hi>Orth. Evang.</hi> Surely this is a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which hath too much affinity with that of the Jeſuites, and Arminians, who imagine that God makes a promiſe, that he will give ſuper-natural Grace to men upon condition they will uſe well their common grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>PROPOSITION II.</hi> That the firſt evidence of our Juſtification, is not any work of Sanctification.</head>
               <p n="1">1. All good works are to be done in Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8. We muſt (as <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rſinus</hi> ſaith) be perſwaded, that both our perſons, and our actions are accepted in and through Chriſt. If this perſwaſion be the cauſe of good Works, there muſt be a ground of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion precedent to our Works. Good Works are the effects of a former evidence: therefore not our firſt evidences.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All Moral Duties are comprehended under this general Precept of Love, by which Faith works, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. as being either the elicite, or imperate acts of Love: but we cannot truly love God, or our neighbor, before we know, and believe the love that God hath to us, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21. Who is righteous (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) but he that requiteth the love of God with love again? Which is never done, except the Holy Ghoſt reveal unto a man by Faith, Gods eternal purpoſe concerning his future Salvation. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 107. If all our acts of evangelical love, flow from the apprehenſion of Gods love to us, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be procreant cauſes of this apprehenſion, nor our firſt evidences.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All that the Goſpel requires of us, is to believe and repent: We cannot evangelically re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent before we perceive in ſome meaſure that God is reconciled unto us in Chriſt, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.63. Wherefore it is not our repentance, nor any work of Sanctification which is our firſt evidence. A man cannot earneſtly apply himſelf to Repentance, unleſs he know himſelf to be of God, <hi>Cato. Inot.</hi> 3.3.2.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:179239:3"/>
               <p n="4">4. All Works of Sanctification are ſo many acts of gratitude, which hath ever relation to ſome former known benefit, and eſpecially our Redemption through Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. This benefit muſt be known by ſome Argument precedent to our works. Therefore Sanctification is not our firſt evidence. <hi>urſinus</hi> makes Gratitude the third part of his Catechiſm, and placeth it after mans miſery, and freedom through Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. All good works muſt be done in the name of Chriſt our Mediator, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.17. in obedience to God our Father. Then are we to know Chriſt to be our Mediator, and God our Father, and ſo by conſequence our juſtification, by ſome Argument antecedaneous to our works.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The appearing of Gods grace which brings Salvation, and of the kindneſs and love of God our Saviour, juſtifying of us by his grace is the cauſe of all our good works, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2, &amp; 3. If the appearing of Juſtification and Salvation to the eye of Faith, be the cauſe of all our San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, then is not Sanctification our firſt evidence.</p>
               <p n="7">7. All good works, from the firſt to the laſt, are to be done without a ſervil fear, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74. This ſear is never removed, but by a precedent ſight of our deliverance from our ſpiritual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: wherefore our Redemption and Juſtification is made known unto us by ſome other means, which goes in order before all works of Sanctification.</p>
               <p n="8">8. To begin to evidence a good eſtate from works, is oppoſite to the method preſcribed by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter.</hi> He did write to Chriſtians, who knew, and believed their juſtification; for believing they rejoyced in joy unſpeakable, and full of glory, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. He exhorts them to add unto their Faith, Vertue, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. This Faith was exiſtent out of its cauſes, not to be grounded upon works, but only confirmed by them. He doth not ſay, Add unto your works faith of aſſurance, but add unto your faith works. Therefore this Faith of aſſurance is not founded upon ſanctification, as a firſt evidence.</p>
               <p n="9">9. We have two diſtinct witneſſes of our good eſtate, which in order do precede our ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. 1 Our inward call of the ſpirit. 2 Our act of believing on the Son of God. The ſpirits inward call, accompanying the outward, begets this act of Faith, 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 5.10. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5. This act of Faith brings forth works of Sanctification, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. Sanctification is in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the laſt of the three witneſſes of a good eſtate, as being the effect of the two former: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not our firſt evidence. <hi>Hoc eſt initium ſalutis noſtrae, quod in nobis ſentimus: efficax interna vocatio Dei, &amp; fides noſtra aſſentiens. Zanchie De Certâ ſalute Eccleſiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> (with other learned and godly Divines, living in that age, wherein the light of the Goſpel did abundantly break forth) defined juſtifying Faith, not only by an act of the Will, whereby we receive Chriſt, and his benefits, but alſo by an act of the Mind, by which we are certainly perſwaded of Gods love to us in Chriſt, and he doth conſtantly deny ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to be our firſt evidence; and in his Commentaries upon <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> calls Works after-proofs, Faiths props. Both he, and <hi>Zanchie,</hi> do acknowledge (with all ſound Divines, and the whole Church) that good works evidence; but with this caution, There muſt be a former evidence. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> thus expreſſeth himſelf, But foraſmuch as of the fruits of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration the Saints gather an Argument, of the Holy Ghoſts dwelling in them, they do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not ſlenderly ſtrengthen themſelves, to look for the help of God in their neceſſities, when by experience, they find him their Father in ſo great a matter. And even this alſo they cannot do, unleſs firſt they have conceived the goodneſs of God, ſealed with no other aſſuredneſs than that of the promiſe; for if they begin to weigh it by good works, nothing ſhall be more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, or more weak, <hi>Inſt.</hi> 3.14.19. <hi>Zanchie</hi> doth declare his judgement in the ſame expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>Loco</hi> 11. <hi>De Juſtificatione. Calvin</hi> upon this text, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.19. <hi>And hereby we know that we are of the truth, and ſhall aſſure our hearts before him:</hi> doth thus Comment; <hi>Semper autem me minerimus, non habere nos, ex charitate notitiam quam dicit Apoſtolus quaſi inde
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179239:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>petenda ſit ſalutis certitude, &amp; certe non aliunde cognoſcimus nos eſſe filios Dei, niſi quia gratuitam ſuam Adoptionem cordibus noſtris per ſpiritum ſuum obſignat: Et nos certum ejus pignus in chriſto oblatum fide amplectimur.</hi> This is the queſtion here determined by Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> How we come firſt to know that we are the Children of God, and by the like reaſon juſtified? He denies that it is by any argument taken from our love. How then? By the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward witneſs of the Spirit, perſwading us of our Adoption. What uſe then are we to make of our love to the Brethren, in point of evidencing? It under props, (ſaith he) and ſtrengthens our perſwaſion. Theſe are his words; <hi>Eſt igitur charitas acceſsio, vel adminiculum inferius al ſidei fulturam, non fundamentum quo nititur. Zanchie</hi> upon <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.1. draws this as an inference from that text; <hi>Sciamus ergo &amp; pro fundamento chriſtianae Pietatis teneamus, hoc primum principium, fidem.</hi> i. <hi>certiſsimam perſwaſionem de remiſsione peccatorum, ex ſolâ paterna clementia condonatorum, cauſam eſſe omnium virtutum, omnium bonorum operum, omniſque verae obedientiae.</hi> They who ſtand for the firſt evidencing of Works overthrow this fundamental principle. The Anſwer which Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> gives to this Queſtion, Whether ſome ſaving qualification may be a firſt evidence of Juſtification? is thus ſet down by himſelf <hi>in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis;</hi> A man may have an Argument from thence, (yea, I doubt not a firm, and ſtrong Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument) but not a firſt evidence. In his Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Baylie,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>Keeping Gods Commandments, and love to the Brethren, are brought in by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> John, <hi>as firſt evidences of Juſtification,</hi> 1 John 2.3. &amp; 3.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe, and the like Scriptures ſtrongly argue, That works of Sanctification are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain evidences of a good eſtate, which is a truth ſo clearly held forth in Gods Word, as if it were written with a beam of the Sun: But can it be concluded from hence, That <hi>John,</hi> and the Chriſtians to whom he wrote (amongſt which they of the loweſt rank did know the Father, had received an unction from the holy One, and knew all things) had no former evidence of their juſtification? Did they never hear the inward witneſs of the Spirit, nor ſee their Falth by which they did receive this witneſs? Did they conclude a good eſtate, by reflecting upon their keeping Gods Commandments, and love to the Brethren, without any immediate diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their inward Call, or their act, or acts of believing, as precedent in order to their works? Whether was this keeping Gods Commandments, and love to the Brethren, the procreant cauſe of their knowing, and believing the love of God to them, or the contrary? The Apoſtle puts it out of doubt, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.16.20. <hi>We know and believe the love that God hath to us:</hi> What effect doth this produce? <hi>We love him becauſe he firſt loved us.</hi> It is our knowing and believing that God loved us firſt, even from eternity, that makes us love him. This is then the Apoſtles meaning, We who have received the Spirit of Adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father, we who are believers, are confirmed in our Faith, becauſe it is operative, and works, cauſing us to keep Gods Commandments, and this ſpecial Commandment of loving the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. What is the keeping of Gods Commandments, but charity out of a pure heart, and Faith unfeined? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. Faith whereby we are truly perſwaded, of Gods mercy towards us in Chriſt, is the mother of a good Conſcience, and charity. What is love to the Brethren, but an holy affection, wrought in us by the Holy Ghoſt, whereby upon the apprehenſion of Gods love to us in Chriſt, we do from our very hearts, wiſh well unto them, and ſtudy to do them all the good we can? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.16.19, 20. Truly we ſhould neither love God, nor the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, nor his Commandments, did he not firſt make known his love in Chriſt to us. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> upon theſe words, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.3. <hi>And hereby we do know that we know him, if we keep his Commandments:</hi> writes thus, <hi>Notandus eſt hic orde. quum dicit, nos cognoſcere quod no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verimus. Significat Dei obedientiam ſic conjunct am eſſe ſcientiae, ut tamen haes ordine fit prior: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cuti neceſſe eſt cauſam effectu ſuo eſſe priorem.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:179239:4"/>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>An Effect argues the Cauſe, as well as the Cauſe doth its Effect; Why may we not begin with keeping Gods Commandments, and love to the Brethren, to evidence a good eſtate, and make them our firſt evidences? We can know by fruit, that there is a tree upon which it did grow; and by ſtreams, that there is a fountain from which they did flow, though we never ſee the tree, or the ſpring.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The tree doth naturally bring forth its fruits, and the fountain ſends out its ſtreams without any act of ours, whether we ſee them, or not: But Juſtification, (which is a gracious act of God, acquitting of us from our ſins, and accepting us as juſt, for the righteouſneſs ſake of Chriſt, received by Faith) doth not cauſe us to bring forth works of Righteouſneſs, and true holineſs, by a meer Phyſical force, but as apprehended by Faith, which works by love, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. The perſwaſion that <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> had of the pardon of her many ſins, made her love much, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.46. If a tree did not bring forth fruit, nor a fountain ſend out water, but by our looking on them, as the inſtrumental cauſe, ſurely we ſhould ſee the tree, as going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fruit, and the ſpring-head before the ſtreams. Good works are ſuch effects, as are cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by our apprehenſion of Gods mercy towards us in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Object. 3. <hi>No man can limit God, to what evidence he ſhall firſt bring into the Conſcience of a juſtified eſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, yet can God limit himſelf: He can do more by his abſolute power, than he doth by that which is actual. If the Lord wil have all works of ſanctification, to be done in Faith, out of love, without a ſlaviſh fear, as ſo many acts of gratitude, for our Redemption through Chriſt, they who deny ſanctification to be the firſt evidence, do not limit God, but are limitted by God. The Goſpel is as immutable in the order, as in the ſubſtance of its parts, being an everlaſting Goſpel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6</p>
               <p>Object. 4. <hi>Many of Gods Children can evidence to themſelves a good eſtate, by their love to God, his children, and commandments, who never were perſwaded of Gods love to them, by any argument taken either from the inward teſtimony of the holy Ghoſt, or their act, or acts of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is aſſerted <hi>gratis,</hi> but not proved. How did thoſe Children of God come unto Chriſt? Surely they were taught of God, and heard the ſpirits inward call. <hi>He that hath heard, and learned of the Father, cometh unto me,</hi> Joh. 6.45. What made them follow Chriſt by Faith, and holy Obedience? It was this inward voyce of the ſpirit, accompanying the outward word, which they did hear, and know. <hi>Chriſts ſheep hear his voyce, and follow him, for they know his voyce,</hi> Joh. 10.3, 4. That which made them believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, was the inward witneſs of the ſpirit. <hi>He that believeth on the Son of God, hath the witneſs in himſelf,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.10. Can it truly be ſaid, That theſe Children of God ſo ſanctified, as they can thereby diſcern their juſtification, did never hear, nor know the ſpirits inward call, nor ſee their ſaith? Can a man love God, or his children, who knows not, (in ſome degree) his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation? A man in the ſtate of nature, hates God, and his children, and this enmity is never ſlain, before peace be revealed, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16, 17. We cannot love the law of God, except we know its rigour, and curſe, to be taken from us through Chriſt. We muſt be delivered from the law, in reſpect of its rigid exaction, and malediction, and that to our apprehenſions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can ſerve, in the newneſs of the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. Suppoſe that Gods true children ſhould ſay, That ſanctification is their firſt evidence, God ſpeaks no ſuch thing in his Word, to the which we muſt rather attend, but the quite contrary, as hath been proved: neither can they reſt in that way of evidencing, who are truly gracious; for the law of grace binds them, firſt to be perſwaded of remiſſion of ſins, and then to ſerve God without fear, from this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, and this law is written in their hearts. If men under the law ſhould glory in their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179239:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>penitency, works of ſanctification, and ſtrict walking, as firſt evidences, they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced <hi>à priori,</hi> becauſe they want this cauſe hereof, <hi>viz.</hi> The apprehenſion of Gods mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them in Chriſt: even as we cut off Enthuſiaſts, Antinomians, Familiſts, Libertines, who boaſt of their full aſſurance, <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> by reaſon they have not the effects, penitency, works of ſanctification, and ſtrict walking. The middle way is the Goſpel way, to wit, from the appearing of Gods grace, to our own ſouls in particular, to deny ungodlineſs, and wordly luſts, to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly, in this preſent world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>PROPOSITION III.</hi> That an act of Faith, which is grounded upon gracious Qualifications, previous to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and Works as firſt evidences, is legal.</head>
               <p>The Works upon which this ſeeming act of Faith is founded, are not evangelical, but legal, which I thus demonſtrate:</p>
               <p n="1">1. After that the Commandment comes, the ſpirit of bondage in the law, we are ſaid to be married to the law, bring forth fruit unto the law, and to ſerve in the oldneſs of the letter, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril we be eſpouſed unto Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7: Before Faith come in the free Promiſe, we are kept under the law, ſchooled, and over-awed by the law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23, 24. We are in bondage under the law, til we receive the adoption of ſons, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.3, 4, 5. Acts done by them, as ſuch, who are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the law, in bondage under the law, muſt needs be legal; and of this nature, are all ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed gracious qualifications before faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Works made firſt evidences, (and that <hi>de jure</hi>) though they go under the name of works of ſanctifitation: yet are they indeed works of the law, becauſe they do not proceed from principles evangelical, but legal.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are not done in Faith, whereby we are perſwaded that our perſons, and our actions are accepted in, and through Chriſt. No, our works muſt firſt be done, and our perſwaſion muſt be the effect of theſe works. We muſt ſee our works accepted, before our perſons.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are not done in Love; for how can we love God, before we know, and believe, the love that he hath to us, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 14 16.19. Our apprehenſion of Gods love, muſt only be an effect of our works, and of ſome imaginal promiſe made to us, in reſpect of theſe our works.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They cannot be acts of Gratitude, for our Redemption through Chriſt. Theſe works muſt be the firſt means, whereby we come to know our Redemption, and juſtification.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are all done out of Bondage, and ſervile Fear. This ſervile fear is never caſt out, but by a ſure perſwaſion of Gods love to us, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.18. And what is the cauſe of this fear, but the ſpirit of bondage? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it doth neceſſarily follow, That a concluſion which doth ſtay it ſelf upon theſe legal <hi>media,</hi> works done out of this fear, is no concluſion of Faith, but (if we may ſo call it) a concluſion of works, being grounded upon works of the law. <hi>Eſtius</hi> (though a Popiſh writer) ſpeaks to this purpoſe upon <hi>Heb</hi> 8.10. <hi>Itaque fatemur, tempore veieris Teſtamenti fuiſſe novi Teſtamenti filios: Et contra tempore Novi Teſtamenti, non paucos cenſeri filios Teſtamenti ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris, videlicet eos omnes, qui carualibus Judaeis ſimiles, timore poenae legem ſervant, imo non ſervant: Sed ſibi ſervare videntur, ut loquitur Auguſt. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>conte.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt. Pel. Cap.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>The Application which I made of this Doctrine, was this for ſubſtance: They who have no more Faith than is built upon gracious qualifications before union, and works made firſt evidences, are under a covenant of works, and though they be never ſo much reformed; yet wil they perſecute them under the covenant of grace, as did <hi>Paul</hi> before his converſion, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179239:5"/>Scribes, Phariſees, &amp;c. Wherefore if any ſhal profeſs themſelves to be legal, and raiſe up per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt you, for this truth, contend earneſtly for it, in a way of patient ſuffering, by the ſword of the ſpirit, the word of God. The Doctrine contained in theſe three Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and this or the like general hupothetical application, was the cauſe of my deep ſufferings. It ſeems that you (Brother <hi>Weld</hi>) with ſome others, who proſecuted againſt me, did build the Faith upon gracious qualifications precedent to union, and works as firſt evidences, I cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure this Doctrine of yours to be legal, as aforeſaid: and hereupon you are filled with indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, caſt me out as the filth of the world, and off-ſcouring of al things, make me a ſpectacle to the world, and to Angels, and to men, which you effect by theſe means.</p>
               <p>About two months after the Preaching of my Sermon, before ever I was dealt withal in a brotherly way, I am ſent for to the Court, to anſwer for what I had delivered; where I have the true cauſe of my ſufferings ſuppreſſed, and put out of ſight, and a feigned cauſe cloſely, and ſecretly brought in.</p>
               <p>Certain of my Brethren, the Reverend Elders, had a great hand in this myſterious buſineſs; for whilſt my cauſe was depending, long before my baniſhment, an Accuſation was ſecretly drawn up againſt me in writing, put into the Court, thus inſcribed:</p>
               <q>The Grounds and Reaſons of the Diſſent of the Elders of the Churches, from ſome things delivered by Mr. <hi>VVhelewright</hi> upon the Faſt-day, which they do here preſent to the Honored Court, and the Churches of Chriſt planted amongſt us, to be conſidered of; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring Grace, Truth, and Peace, from God the Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</q>
               <p>In this Accuſation, I am charged to have delivered theſe Four Points:</p>
               <q>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. That Faith, and Repentance, are no parts of the Doctrine of the Goſpel.</item>
                     <item>II. That to evidence Juſtification by Sanctification, is a covenant of Works.</item>
                     <item>III. That they who ſee in themſelves any Sanctification, and thence conclude a good eſtate, ſhall never be ſaved.</item>
                     <item>IV. They who hold not according to this Doctrine, are Antichriſts, enemies to Chriſt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a covenant of Works.</item>
                  </list>
               </q>
               <p>VVhether my Brethren the Elders dealt regularly, and juſtly with me, either for the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> or <hi>Matter</hi> of this Accuſation, I ſhal now make it appear.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Manner,</hi> I ſhal not much inſiſt upon it; but the truth is, They accuſe me to the Court ſecretly. In the Preface to their Charge, after many bitter invectives, ranking me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the inſtruments of Satan, acted by him, to put down the Kingdom of Chriſt upon earth, becauſe I could not do it in heaven, &amp;c. It is pretended by them, That they do not write ſo much, to aggravate my fault in the eye of Authority, as to convince me in my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and to bring me to Repentance: yet al this while they conceal it from me, neither did I ever come to know of this their writing, more or leſs, by their means, or by the Court, but a Gentleman my Friend, one of the Magiſtrates, did procure a copy to be tranſcribed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly in al haſte, and ſent it unto me.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Matter</hi> of their Accuſation, I ſhal examine the grounds of the ſeveral branches of their Charge:</p>
               <p n="1">I. They inform the Court, That I taught, <hi>That Faith, and Repentance, are no parts of the Doctrine of the Gospel.</hi> The reaſon which they give is, becauſe I ſaid, That in the Goſpel there is nothing revealed but Chriſt. Surely it could not be imagined, that I meant that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is revealed in the whole Goſpel, but this ſimple term Chriſt. The words immediately precedent (which they leave out, taking that abſolutely, which I ſpoke in ſome reſpect) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my ſenſe. When the Lord (ſaid I) draws his Elect to believe in Chriſt, he doth not reveal unto them ſome work, and from that work carrieth them to believe on him, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179239:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>revealed but Chriſt. I exclude qualifications, from that promiſe, wherein Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, offered, given to be believed on, and make it abſolute. How ſhould I deny Faith to be part of the Goſpel, in that diſcourſe, in which my chief ſcope was, to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a legal, and evangelical Faith? The two Deputys Teſtimony, concerning ſome expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which I uſed in a Sermon at the Mount, did not agree, made nothing to the purpoſe. If I had ſpoken ſomething then, from which ſuch a concluſion would follow, (which I never did) can you neceſſarily conclude from thence, That I delivered the ſame in my Sermon at the Faſt, as you accuſe me? As for this Article of your Charge, there is not to be found in my whole Sermon, a ſyllable ſounding that way, <hi>ne gry quidem.</hi> To my beſt remembrance, al that I have ſpoken, taught, written at any time concerning Faith, and Repentance, from which you might take occaſion to draw ſuch a groundleſs inference, was this for ſubſtance:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Faith, and Repentance are law <hi>i. e.</hi> our inherent conformity to the law of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, in oppoſition to the righteouſneſs of the Promiſe, which is Chriſts righteouſneſs, and that only in point of juſtification. I aſſerted herein no more but this, That Faith and Repentance, is not that juſtice for which we are acquitted before God, it is alone, the righteouſneſs of God which is by Faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That theſe conditional Promiſes, <hi>believe, and be ſaved; repent, and be ſaved;</hi> are not proper, and peculiar to the Goſpel, as conditional, but common to the law with the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, though not in reſpect of their matter, yet in regard of their conditional form, to difference them from abſolut promiſes, peculiar to the Goſpel, both for matter, and form.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thoſe conditional Promiſes being made the whole intire Goſpel, by an excluſion of al abſolute Promiſes, without any relation unto them, becomes a covenant of Works for form. A meer conditional covenant is a legal covenant. This is one eſſential difference, between the covenant of Works, and Grace. In the covenant of Works al the Promiſes are meerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional: in the covenant of Grace, with relation to Gods Elect, the Promiſes are either ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, or upon conditions abſolutely promiſed. Will it follow from theſe principles, That I deny the doctrine of Faith, and Repentance to be part of the doctrine of the Goſpel, or the gifts of Faith, and Repentance, to be evangelical Graces? God forbid I ſhould. This is a fundamental Errour of the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> who confounding juſtification, and ſanctification, imagine that Chriſt did as wel perform for us, the conditions of the Goſpel, as the law, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and believing for us. All my conſtant hearers can bear me witneſs, That I have ever Preached, Repentance towards God, and Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. I never denyed theſe conditional Promiſes to be part of the Goſpel, but I deny them to be the whole Goſpel. I do in the name of the Lord (as I am called) exhort al men, not only to believe, but repent, and you amongſt the reſt.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The Second Errour of which you accuſe me is, <hi>That to evidence Juſtification by Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, is a Covenant of Works.</hi> You infer this from theſe expreſſions in the broken Notes, taken by others, (which I owned only for ſubſtance, but not for al expreſſions) that if men think to be ſaved, becauſe they ſee ſome work of Sanctification in themſelves, if they be ſaved, it is without the Goſpel, this is a covenant of works. I ſpake with relation to that which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately went before, to wit, when the Lord is pleaſed to convert any Soul unto himſelf, he doth not reveal unto him ſome work, and from that work carrieth him to believe on Chriſt. All that I affirmed herein was this, To make gracious Qualifications previous to Faith the <hi>media,</hi> to baild that act of Faith upon, by which we believe on Chriſt, is not evangelical, but legal. What though I called them works of Sanctification? I did not mean they were ſuch indeed, but in the opinion of ſome.</p>
               <p n="3">III. This is the Third Errour which you faſten upon me, <hi>That they who ſee in themſelves
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179239:6"/>any Sanctification, and thence conclude a good eſtate, ſhall never be ſaved.</hi> This concluſion is inferred by you from the former Paſſages, in none of which I denyed the evidencing of true Sanctification, but of ſuppoſed Sanctification, as gracious Qualifications before Union, and Works made firſt evidences. You reaſon ſtil from that which is ſpoken in ſome reſpect, to that which is ſpoken abſolutely. You cut off, part of theſe defective Notes, and give ſuch a ſenſe, as the words ſeem to carry conſidered by themſelves, without any Relation to that which goes before, or follows. You diſ-member, wreſt, torture, by putting upon the rack, ſome broken Notes of an extemporary Sermon, and make them ſpeak what you think good againſt the Preacher: and where they are altogether ſilent, and ſpeak not one word, you put in words of your own, which makes for your purpoſe. Let ſuch dealings paſs for current, what Sermon can be Preached by any Miniſter of the Goſpel, which ye may not arraign, accuſe, condemne, baniſh, as guilty of Hereſie, contempt of Authority, Sedition, and what not? No man can ſay with a good Conſcience, That I did at any time, in publick, or private, in Old <hi>England,</hi> or in New, deny true Sanctification to be a good evidence. I look at Works of Sanctification, to be no dubious, nor litigious evidence, but demonſtrative, and infallible, without which the imagined ſpirits witneſs is deluſory, and al ſuppoſed Faith is vain. The Sanctification which I denyed to be any good evidence, are certain effects of the ſpirit of bondage, and works of the law; and I taught, That an act of Faith founded upon them, is not ſaving, and according to the Goſpel, but legal, againſt them, who never knew their inward call, or hear, and learn of the Father, and ſo by Faith come unto Chriſt. The inward witneſs of the Spirit, in a ſimple promiſe of grace, is not immediately, and in it ſelf diſcerned by them, but by their legal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, going under the name of ſanctification.</p>
               <p>Theſe are my apprehenſions concerning our evidencing a good eſtate. The immediate foundation of that act of Faith, by which we are perſwaded, That Chriſt and his benefits is ours, and by which we do receive him, is the free, ſimple, abſolute promiſe of grace, applied by the ſpirit in our effectual call, which is called throughout the Goſpel, by way of excellency, the promiſe, and therefore al Gods children are called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the children of the promiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 8. This Promiſe indeed is indefinite, yet is it determined to every Elect perſon, in his efficacious call. The indefinite Promiſe, with a commandment to believe, and make it particular, comes not in word only, but alſo in Power, and in the holy Ghoſt, from whence he can thus conclude; I am perſwaded to believe by Chriſt, not only outwardly in his words, but inwardly by his Spirit in my heart, that the promiſe, and Chriſt promiſed belongs unto me: therefore Chriſt with al his benefits is mine. The <hi>medium</hi> of the particular Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, of the general Promiſe, is the inward witneſs of the ſpirit of Adoption, who, (as Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> ſaith, in his Sermon, entituled, <hi>Chriſt the true and perfect gain</hi>) beareth witneſs to our conſciences, of ſuch things as God hath given us in particular, and are only in general man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, propunded in the Promiſe. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> grounded his Faith upon this ſimple pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. The indefinite runs thus; <hi>Chriſt loved the world, and gave himſelf for the world. Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners. Paul</hi> applies it, and makes it particular, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſts command) for thus he expreſſeth himſelf, <hi>He loved me, and gave himſelf for me, Gal.</hi> 2.20. Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners, of which I am chief, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. How came <hi>Paul</hi> to make this application? Becauſe he was perſwaded thereunto, not only outwardly in the word, but inwardly by the ſpirit in his heart, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith, That <hi>he that believeth on the Son of God, hath the witneſs in himſelf,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.10. Believing on the Son of God, is the effect; the witneſs in himſelf the cauſe. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> thus expounds it; <hi>Non dicit Deum extra loqui, ſed unumquemque fidelem intus in ſeipſo ſentire, fidei ſuae authorem.</hi> If it be objected, That our firſt act of Faith, cannot be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179239:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>that Chriſt is ours, becauſe he is not ours antecedently to our act of believing, that ſeems to me eaſily to be anſwered. Chriſt unites himſelf unto us by his Spirit, in our effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al call, infuſing the ſeed of Faith, and al other ſaving graces, <hi>is in us, novo modo operandi,</hi> gives us a new heart, and puts his ſpirit within us, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26, 27. Chriſt is ours by a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Reception, antecedently, in order, to our act of believing. Chriſt unites himſelf unto us by his ſpirit, before we joyn our ſelves to him by an act of believing, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. Faith being thus founded, upon the free ſimple promiſe of grace, applied by the ſpirit of promiſe, is confirmed divers wayes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt by works of Sanctification, the immediate proper effects thereof. For though the habit of Faith, be not the cauſe of the habits of other Chriſtian vertues: yet is the act of faith, the ſpirits inſtrument, to produce al acts of ſanctity, as being apprehenſive of Gods grace, mercy, love in Chriſt, and other motives, and perſwaſives, to induce to good works, receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrength from Chriſt, enabling us to perform them. So that true faith works by love, which love, with other Chriſtian vertues, wherein we do reſemble Chriſt, to whom we are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, are unto us a ſeal of that fellowſhip we have with him, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>In whom after ye believed, ye were ſealed with the holy ſpirit of Promiſe,</hi> Epheſ. 1.13. The ſpirit in ſealing of us, imprints in ſome meaſure, the very image of Chriſt upon us, conſiſting in righteouſneſs, and true holineſs, being not only holy in his eſſence, and nature, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his gracious effects in us. All theſe works of Sanctification, are ſo many arguments of the truth of our Faith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.3. &amp; 3.14. They are diſtinguiſhing marks, and put a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt difference between the children of God, and the children of the Devil, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.10. They who do not know God to be their God, as wel by putting his law in their inward parts, and writing it in their hearts, as by forgving their iniquities, were never truly taught of God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33, 34. This is one end of the ſpirits giving, that holy ſpirit, that ſpirit of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, not only to work ſanctification, but to teach us to know it, amongſt other things, which are freely given us of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. This hath been practiſed by <hi>Job, David, Hezekiah, Paul,</hi> and the whole Church of the Elect, believers, and ſaints, from time, to time, in al generations, who, after that they had built their Faith upon Chriſt, revealed, offered, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the free promiſe, did under-prop, confirm, ſtrengthen the ſame, by works of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly by the immediate teſtimony of the holy Ghoſt. There is an inward teſtimony of the ſpirit, common to al true Chriſtians, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.16. which, I take, to be an act of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, applying the Goſpel with ſuch power, as we perceive it is the ſpirit who ſpeaks, and it be gets in us an affured Faith, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5. This is immediate, in, and by the word of grace: for of his own wil begat he us, with the word of truth, <hi>James</hi> 1.10. The immediate teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is, (I conceive) an act of the ſpirit, by which he doth dictate, and ſtrongly ſuggeſt, with a ſoul-raviſhing inward voyce, to a believing, penitent, humble, over-coming Saint, that he is the child of God, his ſins are forgiven, or the like, being compared to hidden Manna, a white ſtone, a new name, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. which doth exceedingly confirm Faith, and it is not (I ſuppoſe) the portion of every good Chriſtian, but a ſpecial benefit given by God, who is a moſt free agent, before, in, or after ſufferings for the name ſake of Chriſt, or ſome ſpecial ſervice done unto him, as God ſees meet. Sundry of our learned, godly, orthodox Divines do acknowledge ſuch a teſtimony, as Dr. <hi>Preſton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Elton,</hi> with others: and divers of the Martyrs had experience thereof, as (I doubt not) many Chriſtians have at this day. This is part of the Comforters office, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that which is taught in the Word, he ſhal bring to remembrance, <hi>John</hi> 14.26. The ſpirit of truth, never revealeth any thing in this kind immediately, for the confirmation of Faith, which is not revealed, in the words of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179239:7"/>truth. <hi>He ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>he ſhall take of mine, and ſhew it unto you,</hi> Joh. 16.13, 14. This immediate Teſtimony differs not from that which is mediate by the Word, in the thing teſtified, but in the manner of teſtifying, and ſtabliſheth the Soul, by making a deeper impreſſion, filling it with joy, and with the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By ſpiritual ſenſe, and experience: There is in Gods Children, not only <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.9. By reaſon of uſe, they have their ſenſes exerciſed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. and that by divine objects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are many times made very ſenſible of the grace, mercy, and love of God unto them in Chriſt. The love of God is ſhed abroad in their hearts, by the holy Ghoſt which is given unto them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. The Lord doth again and again lift upon them the light of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and in the light of his favour, they ſee the light of all felicity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36 9. Chriſt doth manifeſt himſelf unto them in the Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.21. They hear, ſee, look upon, and handle the word of life, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. They taſte, and ſee that the Lord is good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They have frequently, and for the moſt part, as of ſin, ſo likewiſe of the work of Gods grace in them, ſenſe and experience. The wind of the Spirit blows into the gardens of their Souls, and the ſpices of ſaving graces, with a fragrant ſmell flow out, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16. The Sun of Righteouſneſs ſhines into the hearts of Beleevers, acts upon the ſaving graces of his own ſpirit, excites, and ſtirs them up, from whence a ſweet ſcent goes out, as from ſome coſtly perfumed Oyntment. When Faith, love, joy, godly ſorrow for ſin, humility, patience, with other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving graces, are vigourouſly acted, it exceedingly affects the Saints, who are very ſenſible of it.</p>
               <p>The Virgins love Chriſt, not only for the ſavour of the oyntment of his own Righteouſneſs, which they perceive, and receive by faith, but even of theſe good oyntments powred into them, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. The <hi>Spouſe</hi> in the <hi>Canticles, David, Paul,</hi> with others, do largely expreſs the great ſenſe, and feeling they had, of the gifts of Gods Spirit in them, accompanying ſalvation, as an Argument of that fellowſhip which they had with Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Beleevers have an experimental knowledge of the gracious Works of Gods Providence about them, which doth likewiſe confirm their Faith. So had <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 17.37. So had <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.17, 18 For though there be no marks ſet upon the outward acts of Gods Providence, whereby they may be diſcerned, to proceed from Gods eternal, and fatherly love, yet do the children of God behold them, in, and through the covenant of Grace, as teſtimonies of Gods favour, and feel them to be ſuch, by their gracious effects, knowing by experience, that chaſtiſements, and corrections for ſin are for their good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71. So that the long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience which we have of Gods grace upon us, his work of grace in us, the gracious works of his providence about us, is a ſpecial means to ſtrengthen our faith.</p>
               <p>This, (for the ſubſtance) is all that I have ever Taught, or held forth concerning eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing a good eſtate. I am not for the ſole witneſſing of the Spirit, with Enthuſiaſts, nor of Faith alone, with Solifidians, nor of works in the firſt place, with you: but of al theſe Three in one, and that in the Apoſtles order, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. The Spirits inward effective teſtimony of Gods grace towards us in Chriſt, in giving him unto us, in the free ſimple promiſe, with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to beleeve, begets faith, faith produceth works of ſanctification, ſanctification con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms faith. Promiſes are ſo many Declarations of Gods good Will towards us, and it is the ſpirits office to apply them. I do humbly conceive, That when the Spirit of Promiſe applyes the abſolute Promiſe of Grace, that by way of excellency, is called The ſpirits witneſs; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I do not ſee, how the ſpirits witneſs ſhould be a diſtinct witneſs from water, and blood: If the conditional Promiſe made to beleeving be applied, that is the witneſs of blood; let the conditional Promiſe made to ſanctification, have its application, that is the witneſs of water: He who hath one of theſe three witneſſes, hath them all in ſome degree; and he that wants
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179239:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>one, wants them all: for all theſe three are brought in by Chriſt, when he comes into our hearts, in our effectual call, as witneſſes of his gracious preſence. So that a Chriſtian can rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus; I have the ſpirits witneſs, I am a beleever, I am a Saint; therefore Chriſt dwells in me, and I in him. This is the ſum of all concerning Evidencing; That act of Faith by which we beleeve that Chriſt, and his Righteouſneſs is given to us, and we receive him, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by the inward teſtimony of the ſpirit, in an abſolute promiſe, confirmed by works of ſanctification, the immediate teſtimony of the holy Ghoſt, ſpiritual ſenſe, and experience. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not acknowledge your works to be good Evidences, which you will needs have to appear, before Gods Grace, or Faith appear, you are highly diſpleaſed, and labour to make the Court, Churches, and all the world beleeve, that I taught, That ſanctification is no good Evidence, and if a man conclude a good eſtate from ſanctification, which he ſees in himſelf, he ſhall never be ſaved.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Fourth Errour which you charge me to have delivered is; <hi>That they who hold not according to this Doctrine, are Antichriſtians, enemies to Chriſt, and under a Covenant of Works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If by this Doctrine you had meant, That Doctrine which indeed I taught, owned by me in my firſt Three Propoſitions, you had done me wrong. I did never expreſly, nor implicitly affirm; That they who were not of my judgement, about the grounds of a ſpecial Faith, or order of evidencing, were under a covenant of Works; I was not ſo cenſorious. I doubt not but many of your judgment, who are truly gracious, having an internal principle of true faith, byaſſing their ſpirits another way, than they diſcern. The perſons ſo judged by me, were ſuch as walked, and only walked according to that judgement which I condemend, not only Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retically, but Practically. But ſeeing by this Doctrine you underſtand, that Heretical, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Doctrine, contained in the three former parts of your Accuſation, which you have fathered upon me fallaciouſly, without any juſt cauſe, it is a double injury, and this member of your charge, muſt needs vaniſh away, with the reſt of your deviſed calumnies, putting a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſenſe, upon certain expreſſions, in the Notes of my Sermon, contrary to all rules of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, divine, and humane.</p>
               <p>This ground-work being thus ſecretly laid, in the concluſion, I am cenſured by the major<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of the Court, to baniſhment, as guilty of thoſe two crimes, Contempt of Authority, and Sedition. That I was juſtly condemned, and cenſured by the court, is that which you, in your ſhort ſtory, endeavour to prove, but by what evidence of reaſon, and force of arguments, falls now into conſideration, to be examined, and diſcuſſed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, You go about to prove <hi>that I was guilty of Contempt of Authority, becauſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>I did not ſtudy Truth, and Peace, which Authority required.</hi> Contempt is an act of the mind, whereby we little, or not at all regard a thing: Contempt of Authority is when a man doth willingly refuſe to ſubmit to the promulgated juſt Laws, or lawful known commands of Magiſtrates, as ſuch, and hereupon proceeds to do ſomething contrary to thoſe laws and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. I know no law, or command prohibiting me to Preach what I delivered: Neither do I ſee, how any ſuch law could be juſt: and it will be a difficult thing for you to prove, That I acted from obſtinacy of Will, and ſuch a defect of the Mind. I have already proved the truth of my Doctrine, and that I endeavoured to bring my Heaters to conſent to that Doctrine, cannot be denied; ſo that herein I ſtudied truth, and peace. Peradventure ſome Magiſtrates, and Elders, intended that I ſhould not Preach againſt gracious qualifications before union, and the firſt evidencing of Works, but rather to have cryed down the contrary Doctrine, as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomianiſme, and Familiſm: and becauſe I did not Preach according to their Minds, this is looked at as contempt of Authority. If to preach true Doctrine, and unite men in the truth,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179239:8"/>contrary to the intent of ſome Magiſtrates, and Elders, be contempt of Authority, ſurely the Prophets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles were notorious delinquents, and guilty of this crime. You ſpeak of other contemptuous carriages, but inſtance in no particulars. I came one day tardy to the Court, of which you tell all the world, but that was from miſ-information, not out of any contempt. I uſed ſome expreſſions of an acquitting glorying conſcience, when I ſuffered ſuch ſhame in your Aſſemblies, and did diſpiſe that ſhame, and ſo did he who was free enough from contempt of Authority, <hi>endure the Croſs, despiſing the ſhame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In the ſecond place you undertake to make it good, <hi>That I was guilty of Sedition, by theſe Arguments:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt (ſay you) <hi>I inflamed the minds of men one againſt another, cauſed diviſions, made breaches.</hi> All this was accidental. The word of God is a fire, a ſword, and hammer to inflame, divide, break in pieces. If ſimply to make diviſions were Sedition, it would more ſtrongly conclude againſt Chriſt than <hi>Barrabas.</hi> Your Arguments taken from Ethnick partial deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Sedition, are of no force againſt Chriſtians. Sedition is a dividing civil Societies, as they are combin'd together, in an unity of juſtice, and common utility. My Diviſion was not Civil, but Spiritual. I did not go about to divide in that which was juſt, and profitable, but in that Errour of gracious Qualifications before Union, and Works firſt Evidencing. <hi>Paul</hi> was accuſed by <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Orator, for <hi>a peſtilent fellow, and a mover of Sedition,</hi> upon the like ground.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, You Object, <hi>That I laid moſt of the Magiſtrates, and Elders, under a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works.</hi> To lay men under a covenant of Works ſimply in it ſelf, is not any tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion Political, Moral, or Evangelical. The Syllogiſme which concluded the Elders under that covenant, was this; <hi>They who walk in that way deſcribed by me to be a Covenant of Works, are under that Covenant. But the Elders Walk in that way deſcribed by me, to be a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works. Therefore the Elders are under that Covenant.</hi> Upon much queſtioning in the Court, the <hi>major</hi> was made by me; upon a queſtion put by the Court to the Elders, the <hi>minor</hi> was brought into Court, in writing, by them. The <hi>Concluſion</hi> was made by the Court. My <hi>Propoſition</hi> was conditional, or equipollent thereunto, and <hi>conditionalis prepoſitio nihil ponit in eſſe, ſeu nihil certe affirmat.</hi> The Elders aſſumption made it abſolute. The Argument by which I deſcribed a man under a covenant of Works, were the internal motions of his ſpirit, known only to God, and his own conſcience, and the Argument <hi>ſub unâ, &amp; utrâque,</hi> is not <hi>à pari.</hi> In a word, I did not ſo much as in my thoughts, conclude the Magiſtrates, and Elders, or any one of them, or any other perſon, abſolutely to be under that covenant. This conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, The Magiſtrate, and Elders are under a covenant of Works, cannot be deduced from any thing delivered by me, without the Elders Aſſumption, in which I had no hand. This was the Courts frequent, and main Objection againſt me, <hi>That I laid them, and the Elders under a Covenant of Works.</hi> I deſired to know of them in what line, or page, proteſting that I neither expreſſed, nor intended any ſuch thing. Far be it from me to take Gods Office out of his hand, who is the ſearcher of the heart, and the tryer of the reins of all men. If the Elders Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and the Courts Concluſion be removed, there remains nothing for me to ſuffer for, but only my Propoſition, which (it ſeems) did <hi>pungere,</hi> and cut deep. If it cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of my Sermon, that I ſaid, the Magiſtrates, Elders, and moſt of the Country, were under a Covenant of Works, &amp;c. I am innocent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, You Reaſon from <hi>the Seditious Effects of my Sermon.</hi> I do not know any fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Seditious practiſes; But if there were any ſuch, they are not to be called <hi>Effects,</hi> but <hi>Events.</hi> That is put for a cauſe, which is no cauſe I do not ſee any innate force in my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, to produce any Effects, but theſe; 1. To draw the Hearers from your Tenants about
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179239:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Faiths grounds, both in judgement, and practiſe. 2. To Unite them in that judgement, and practiſe, which I apprehended to be evangelical. 3. To contend by Arguments, and ſufferings with ſuch as did profeſs themſelves to be legal, perſecuting them for the Truth herein, in caſe any ſuch ſhould ariſe. Might not all this have been done without <hi>Sedition? Tertullian</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, That the Gentiles uſed to fall upon Chriſtians in time of publick Calamity. If <hi>Tiber</hi> and <hi>Nilus</hi> did not over-flow, if the heavens reſtrained their influence, if there were Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, Wars, Famine, Peſtilence, as the cauſe of all thoſe evils, whenas indeed the cauſe was in themſelves.</p>
               <p n="4">4. You make a great matter of certain typical, &amp; allegorical expreſſions, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I uſed to ſet forth our ſpiritual combate, taken from bodily fightings, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> you would have to be underſtood in their literal, &amp; proper ſenſe, as if I ſhould ſtir up to a bodily fight. You confeſs that I did otherwiſe expreſs my meaning, &amp; why wil not you take my meaning as I did expreſs it? Why might not I uſe ſcripture expreſſions in a ſcripture ſenſe? To cut off all your Arguments at once; all this while you diſpute <hi>ex non conceſſis.</hi> You have grounded the Courts ſentence, Cenſure, &amp; all your reaſons to maintain the juſtice of the Court, upon the matter contained in that ſecret Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before mentioned, which did never ſhew its face openly, but acted <hi>in tenebris.</hi> Brother <hi>Weld,</hi> you would have your Hearers to take it for granted, That I delivered that which you char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged upon me in your Accuſation, to which you relate all your defence of the Courts juſtice. You lay this as a ground-work, as will appear by ſundry paſſages in that which you call a ſhort ſtory, but eſpecially in your Preface to it. Theſe are your words; <hi>Now you might hear one of them Preach a moſt dangerous Sermon in a great Aſſembly; when he divided the whole Country into two rancks, ſome (that were of his opinion) under a Covenant of Grace; &amp; thoſe were friends to Chriſt: Others, under a Covenant of Works, whom they might know by this, if they did evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence their good eſtate by ſanctification: Theſe were</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Enemies to Chriſt, Herods, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Scribes, Phariſees, yea, Antichriſts.</hi> I confeſs, if this were true, I had deſervedly ſuffered. But I pray you Mr. <hi>Weld,</hi> let me come a little cloſer unto you: With what good conſcience can you report theſe things? Firſt, That which you relate is not contained in the Notes of my Sermon, which I ſuppoſe, are upon record in the Court of the <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi> in <hi>New England,</hi> neither immediately, nor in their principles. Secondly, After your Accuſation before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned came to my hands, I ſent an Anſwer to you Elders, which you received, ſhewing my ſelf much grieved with that your clandeſtine, unparalled practiſe, diſclaiming theſe Errours which you charged upon me, as erronious, and wicked, ſhewing that you had no ground to father them upon me. Thirdly, I was queſtioned in the Court about theſe particulars: Firſt, They asked me, <hi>Whether Faith, and Repentance were any Conditions of the Goſpel?</hi> I Anſwered, They were Conditions conſequent, but not antecedent; that is, they followed Chriſts giving of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto us in a free promiſe, but went not before. Secondly, They demanded of me, <hi>Whether Sanctification was any Evidence of a good Eſtate?</hi> Yes; (ſaid I) it is ſecondary evidence, but not the firſt. Thirdly, The Court put this Queſtion to me, <hi>Whom I meant of by thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Covenant of Works?</hi> To which I Replyed, I intend it of none abſolutely, but conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, if they walk in that way which I deſcribe to be legal. I did openly in the Court, and I doubt not, in your hearing, plainly expreſs my ſenſe, and meaning. Fourthly, Reverend Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> who conſtantly in the Court ſtood by me, &amp; with me, in a ſpeech which he made, bears this witneſs to the Doctrine I taught, <hi>I do conceive, and profeſs, That our Brother</hi> Whele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrights <hi>Doctrine is according to God, in the Points controverted, and wholly, and altogether, and nothing did I hear alleaged againſt the Doctrine, proved by the Word of God.</hi> Would that learned, judicious, holy man of God give ſuch teſtimony to that Doctrine, delivered by me, or would you have ſuffered it in him, if it had been according to your Report? Certainly he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179239:9"/>would have abhorred it, and born as much witneſs againſt it as you. Miſerable is that cauſe which cannot be juſtified, without ſuch feigned Accuſations, againſt ſo much light. Will theſe their Fictions juſtifie the Courts acts? To ſet a fairer colour upon your cauſe, and make it more probable that I was juſtly condemned, and cenſured by the Court, you do in your ſhort ſtory take this courſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, You put upon me many odious, and reproachful Names: I am ſtiled by you an Antinomian, Familiſt, Libertine, Seducer; My conſcience bears me witneſs, That I do not hold (ſo far as I know) any opinion of Sectaries, as ſuch, nor any Doctrine condemned in any approved Council, or Synod, but ſuch as is maintained by ſome Orthodox Divines, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſonant from the Harmony of Churches Confeſſions, though I do not build my Faith upon the Dictates of men, but only upon the written Word of God. I am not (through Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy) an Antinomian, Familiſt, Libertine, or any other Sectary, but a Chriſtian. I do (with Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>) prefer the Papiſts before them: Mr. <hi>Weld</hi> would drown me in that Pit of Hereſies which was privily digged for me.</p>
               <p>The Points of Doctrine which I held, wherein I did really differ from my Reverend Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, in matters of greateſt concernment, were (ſo far as I know) only theſe Five following Poſitions:
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>That to conclude that Chriſt belongs unto us from Qualifications precedent to Union is legal, and no concluſion of Faith.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>That to conclude a good eſtate from Works, as firſt evidences of our union, is legal, and no concluſion of Faith.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>That the Faith of Gods Elect by which they do believe on Chriſt, is grounded upon an abſolute promiſe of grace.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>That the firſt evidence of Gods grace and mercy in giving of us Chriſt, is the inward witneſs of the spirit, in an abſolute promiſe of Grace.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>That in our paſsive converſion, we are juſtified by a paſsive reception of Chriſt, prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently (in order of nature) to our act of beleeving.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>If I may juſtly be branded for an Antinomian, Libertine, Familiſt, Seducer, by reaſon of the Aſſertions, or ſuch as are dependent upon them, I cannot juſtifie my ſelf: yet let me be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that they, or any of them, are erronious, I ſhall by Gods grace retract. <hi>Errare poſſum Haereticus eſſe nolo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, You would make your Reader beleeve, <hi>page</hi> 25. That in the Synod I diſputed, and maintained theſe Points contained in your Charge, which you call the ground-work of my imagined Sedition. You know very well, Brother <hi>Weld,</hi> that long before the Synod in my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Elders, I diſowned them as wicked Errours ſhewing that they were your groundleſs Inferences, and is it likely I ſhould defend them in the Synod? There was no ſuch matter. The Poſitions which I brought into the Synod, (to my beſt knowledge) were theſe enſuing, which I ſhall explicate, and confirm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="thesis">
               <head>
                  <hi>THESIS, I.</hi> That Aſsurance of Justification from Works of Sanctification, is not our Aſſurance of Faith.</head>
               <p>Aſſurance of Faith may be taken in a Twofold ſenſe; 1. Largely, for whatſoever aſſurance we have of Gods ſpecial love to us in Chriſt, from Scripture-grounds, in which ſenſe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion deduced from true Works of Sanctification, is a concluſion of Faith, beleeved in its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, or one of them; the other being known by ſpiritual ſenſe. The witneſs which the ſpirit gives in a conditional promiſe, is as true, as that which he bears in an abſolute promiſe. No
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179239:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>man living (ſaith <hi>Vega</hi>) ſhould ever draw me to doubt of my being in the ſtate of Grace, if I might infer it out of two Propoſitions, the one beleeved, and the other made ſome way evident unto me. <hi>2ly.</hi> Aſſurance of Faith may be taken ſtrictly, and properly, for our firſt perſwaſion we have of Gods mercy towards us in Chriſt. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5 This diſtinction is in uſe amongſt Proteſtant Writers, and the Papiſts underſtand them in this ſenſe. Certainty (ſaith Mr. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi>) is either of Faith, or Experimental, which Papiſts call Moral. Certainty by Faith is to apply the promiſe of ſalvation to our ſelves, and to beleeve without doubting, that remiſſion of ſins belongs unto us. Moral certainty is that which proceeds from Works of ſanctification, as ſigns and tokens of true Faith. <hi>Treat. of Con. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth acknowledge this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral certainty, with this difference from us, That it is only conjectural: but he will by no means admit of that abſolute perſwaſion, precedent to our works, calling it the <hi>Lutheran</hi> preſumption. They (ſaith he) will have their certainty to go before their works, and not to follow them. <hi>Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>De Juſtificatione.</hi> So that in this <hi>Theſis:</hi> I do not deny ſimply, that we have any aſſurance of Juſtification from our works of ſancttification, (far be it from me,) but that the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance which we have from our works, is our firſt perſwaſion of Gods Grace, and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us in Chriſt, which properly, in ſtrictneſs of ſpeech, is called an aſſurance of Faith, is denied by me. In which reſpect I ſaid in my <hi>Sermon,</hi> That our firſt perſwaſion of Gods love was not by faith it ſelf. 1. By faith as an argument, though it be by faith as an organ, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument. Conſonant to this is that which is affirmed by <hi>Zanchy</hi> in his diſpute with <hi>Mazhac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> about the order of evidencing our election, <hi>page</hi> 361. Thus he writes; <hi>Quis hic non videat apertè qualis fuerit ſententia Buceri in hâc materiâ? Nimirum, ut incipiamus à priori, id eſt, contemplatione ſoluis divinae bonitatis, &amp; gratiae in Chriſto oblatae &amp; in Evangelio reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latae: Et inde certam perſuaſionem concipiamus, nos vere fuiſſe ad aeternam ſalutem electos, ideoque; nunc efficaciter vocari. Deinde deſcendamus ad id, quod etiam revera eſt poſterius, nimirnm ad certum fidem, aſſenſum, &amp; obſequium vocanti praebendum.</hi> This is all which I do herein aſſert, That our firſt perſwaſion of Gods mercy towards us in Chriſt, is not founded upon any arguments taken from our works of ſanctification, which I have aboundantly proved in my ſecond Propoſition, whether I refer the Reader.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="thesis">
               <head>
                  <hi>THESIS, II.</hi> That Juſtification goes in order before our Beleeving.</head>
               <p>Juſtification by a paſſive Faith, goes in order of Nature before our act of beleeving, which is thus confirmed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We have the Spirit of Adoption, are made partakers of divine Nature, become new creatures, before we put forth any act of Faith, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12, 13. This is Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vins</hi> Note upon this 13. <hi>verſ. Negat Evangeliſta poſſe quemquam credere niſi qui ex Deo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus eſt.</hi> Now whereas it ſeems by the twelfth <hi>verſe</hi> that we are not the ſons of God, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to our act of beleeving, he doth thus anſwer it; In reſpect of our ſenſe we do not begin to be the ſons of God, but after faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are no ſooner living in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> but his ſin is imputed unto us, before we commit any actual ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. and by the like reaſon, as ſoon as we live in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> his righteouſneſs is imputed unto us, before we put forth any act of righteouſneſs. As in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Generation all men are born ſinners, even by imputation: So in ſpiritual regeneration, all men are born righteous, having the righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If we be not juſtified antecedently to our act of beleeving, then can a man in the ſtate of condemnation, do that eminent work of God, to beleeve on Chriſt, whereas except we be in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179239:10"/>Union with Chriſt, and ſo by conſequence in the ſtate of Grace, we can do nothing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. To Beleeve is the act of a Perſon either in the ſtate of Grace, or in the ſtate of condemnation. Not of condemnation; therefore of grace, and we are juſtified before our act of Faith.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Elect Infants dying before they come to years of diſcretion, or ſanctified in their Mothers Wombs, are juſtified by the habit of Faith: Perſons in this ſtate of Grace being <hi>adulti,</hi> ceaſe not to be juſtified when they fall into ſownes, or otherwiſe put forth no act of Faith, which, (I ſuppoſe) would follow, were they not juſtified by the ſeed of Faith. If the ſeed failed in ſuch a caſe, ſo much as the act doth, by what band ſhould they be united unto Chriſt? And how could perſons out of union with Chriſt be juſtified? The <hi>Belgick</hi> Profeſſors in the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> give this as a reaſon, Why the Faith by which we are firſt converted, and from which we are called Beleevers, is not an act but an habit infuſed of God, becauſe otherwiſe, oft upon one and the ſame day, we ſhould be Beleevers, and Unbeleevers; the children of God, and the children of the Devil. It would (I conceive) upon the ſame ground follow, That were we not juſtified by rhe habit of Faith, but only by the act, we ſhould many times be ſucceſſively juſtified, and unjuſtified. <hi>Chamier</hi> thus expreſſeth himſelf, I ſay it is moſt true, That juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Faith doth follow, if not in time, yet in order juſtification. Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> ſaith in his <hi>New Covenant, page</hi> 55. A man is as paſſive in regeneration, as in his firſt generation; only God giveth his ſpirit, that doth unite us unto Chriſt, which is received by Faith, together with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, and Juſtification: and yet by the act of Beleeving we are juſtified alſo, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. that is manifeſted to be juſtified in our own conſciences.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>This is againſt the judgement of our Orthodox Divines, who generally make Faith an inſtrumental cauſe of our Juſtification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They who do affirm, That in our active converſion, we perceive, and receive Chriſt by an act of Faith, do not deny a paſſive reception precedent to that act, in our converſion, wherein we are altogether paſſive.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>The Scripture never ſaith, That we are juſtified by the habit of Faith, but rather by the act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scripture doth not ſay, That we are juſtified by the habit, or act of Faith <hi>in terminis,</hi> but in ſenſe. Theſe are frequent Goſpel expreſſions, We are juſtified by Faith. Faith is taken as well for the habit, as the act. When Faith is ſaid not to fail, that is to be underſtood of the habit: When we are commanded to Beleeve, that is meant of the act. <hi>Bucer</hi> (ſaith <hi>Zanchy</hi>) is not aſhamed to ſay, That we beleeve ſometimes in act, ſometimes only in habit, There is no condemnation to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus. Let a man be in Chriſt, whether by the act, or by the habit of Faith, he is juſtified. Which way ſoever Chriſt, and his righteouſneſs is made ours, this righteouſneſs is counted to us for ours by God, who counts things as they are.</p>
               <p>Object. 3. <hi>He that beleeveth not, is condemned already,</hi> Joh. 3.18. <hi>We are not then juſtified, but conſequently to our act of beleeving.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The act of Faith doth ever follow the habit, and in order of time, they can ſcarce be diſtinguiſhed the one from the other: But in order of cauſality, Gods work goes before ours. A Chriſtian is in the order of nature, in the ſtate of grace before Faiths act, though not in time. In a word, when it is ſaid, <hi>He that beleeveth not, is condemned already;</hi> it muſt be underſtood thus: He that beleeveth not either <hi>actu ſecundo,</hi> or <hi>actu primo,</hi> elſe what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us when we are aſleep, and put forth no act of beleeving?</p>
               <p>Object. 4. <hi>If we be juſtified antecedently to our act of Faith, then juſtification goes before vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, contrary to that</hi> Rom. 8.30. <hi>And whom he called, them he alſo juſtified.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:179239:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That doth not follow; Vocation is a gracious act of God, by which we are brought into fellowſhip with Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. We are in our effectual call, drawn into union with Chriſt, by a Phyſical act of God, in our paſſive converſion, precedently to our act of beleeving. Faith goes in order before juſtification, both in our paſſive, and active converſion: the habit in the one, and both habit, and act in the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="thesis">
               <head>
                  <hi>THESIS, III.</hi> That the Faith of Gods Elect, whereby they do beleeve on Chriſt, is grounded upon a free, ſimple, abſolute promiſe of Grace.</head>
               <p>The Queſtion is, Whether God in the Goſpel do firſt reveal his ſpecial love to his Elect, in giving of them Chriſt, and bleſſing through him, in a conditional promiſe, or in an abſolute promiſe? I ſay in an abſolute. Theſe are my <hi>Arguments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Almighty God himſelf, the Prophets, Angels, <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, in the publiſhing of the Goſpel, have ever propounded Chriſt to be beleeved on, in an abſolute promiſe of Grace, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19, 20. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Elect have alwayes founded that act of Faith, by which they did beleeve on Chriſt, upon this principle, <hi>Abraham</hi> beleeved on the Lord, and it was counted unto him for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. Upon what promiſe did he ground his Faith? Upon this abſolute promiſe, <hi>Thus ſhall thy Seed be,</hi> Gen. 15.5, 6. This Faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> is made a patern for all the ſpiritual ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> to follow, <hi>Rom</hi> 4.23, 24, 25. <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribeth the Faith by which he ſpiritually lived, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. In what Promiſe was Chriſt revealed? Even in this abſolute Declaration of Gods good Will towards him: <hi>who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi> The Apoſtle tells us, That all the Elect are born as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was: Now we Brethren, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was, are the children of the Promiſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.28. In what form runs the Promiſe? This is the word of Promiſe; <hi>At this time I will come, and</hi> Sarah <hi>ſhall have a Son,</hi> Rom 9.9. The children of this abſolute Promiſe are counted for the ſeed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The proper immediate effects of juſtifying Faith, do ſtrongly argue, That it is built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an abſolute promiſe powerfully applyed by the ſpirit, in our effectual call. How comes Faith to work by Love? It apprehends Gods love to us in Chriſt. How doth it cauſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing? It beholds Chriſt given for us, and to us out of Gods eternal love: <hi>Abraham</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced to ſee Chrtſts day, and he ſaw it, and was glad, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.56. How doth it beget Peace? It looks at God as reconciled unto us in Chriſt. How doth it cauſe Repentance? It makes us apprehenſive that we have ſinned againſt our Saviour. <hi>Omnium appetitivorum motuum cauſa eſt bonum, vel malum apprehenſum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. As in Conjugal Contracts amongſt us, the Husband doth firſt make known his Love, and expreſs his abſolute conſent: ſo doth Chriſt when he doth betroth the Church of his Elect unto himſelf in their effectual Call. <hi>I will ſay unto them that were not my People, Thou art my People, and they ſhall ſay, thou art my God,</hi> Hoſ. 2.23.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If our Faith be not founded upon an abſolute Promiſe, then is not the Covenant of Grace eſtabliſhed upon better Promiſes (for form) than the Covenant of Works, contrary to that which is affirmed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. The New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Promiſes are better than the Old, in this reſpect amongſt the reſt, That they are abſolute, or upon conditions abſolutely promiſed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The abſolute Promiſes are either only to be propounded to Beleevers antecedently; or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179239:11"/>elſe alſo to Unbeleevers for the begetting of Faith: But they are not only to be propounded to Beleevers antecedently. They were no Beleevers, to whom the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> applies the abſolute Promiſes, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19, 20. being ſuch as were unmarried, and not betrothed to what end did he propound them, if not to build faith upon?</p>
               <p n="7">7. There is no conditional Promiſe, or Grant in all the Word of God, wherein Chriſt doth convey himſelf over to us, for the beginning of Salvation. Chriſt doth abſolutely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to give us a new heart, inhabit in us his Spirit, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26, 27. What ever the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrants ſay, to put in any condition, is againſt Scripture and Reaſon. Wherefore we muſt beleeve on Chriſt, and receive him as given in an abſolute Promiſe of Grace. This ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Doctrine which teacheth us to ground our faith, whereby we are perſwaded of Gods Love to us in Chriſt, upon an abſolute Promiſe, is maintained by <hi>Zanchy</hi> in his <hi>Miſcellanies</hi> againſt <hi>Marbuchius,</hi> who objects againſt it as one of <hi>Zanchy</hi>'s Errors, and new Revelations: but he doth earneſtly contend for the truth hereof, affirming of it to be the Judgment of <hi>Bucer,</hi> and that conformable to the Scriptures. Which he could not but imbrace, proving it by Four Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and Anſwers three Objections. The Definition of Juſtifying Faith, given by Dr. <hi>Zanchy,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> declares them to be of this mind: Faith (ſay they) is a ſtedfaſt and aſſured knowledg of Gods kindneſs towards us, which being grounded upon the truth of the free Promiſe in Chriſt, is both revealed to our minds, and ſealed in our hearts, by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. They make two Eſſential parts of Faith, 1. An apprehenſion of Gods Love to us in Chriſt, which is an act of the Intellect. 2. A receiving and imbracing of Chriſt, which is an act of the Will: And they ground both theſe Acts upon a free Promiſe of Grace, effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly applied by the Holy Ghoſt. Theſe are the words of Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> upon <hi>Gal</hi> 3.7. <hi>Faith is not an imagination of our own forging: it is an aſſuredneſs which we conceive of Gods Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when he cometh unto us, and uttereth familiarly his love that he beareth to us.</hi> This hath been the conſtant Definition of Juſtifying Faith, given by our Orthodox Divines in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, and of many ſince: <hi>Fides eſt certa perſuaſio, et</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>quâ cum ſervatorem am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectimur hâc fiduciâ, quod crucifixus, &amp; mortuus ſit in propitiationem pro peccatis, non aliarum tantum, ſed et meis. Melanchthon, Beza,</hi> with many others, deſcribe Faith after that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and generally, this is part of the deſcription of it: <hi>Faith is a certain perſwaſion of Gods mercy towards us in Chriſt;</hi> which they could not do, did they not ground it upon an abſolute Promiſe. All our Expoſitors of the Creed, who make this part of the meaning of that Article, <hi>I beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to be, <hi>I beleeve that Chriſt is mine,</hi> and place it before that act of the heart, by which we rely on Chriſt, do found it upon an abſolute Promiſe. Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Expoſition of the <hi>Creed,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That no man can put his confidence in God, till he be firſt perſwaded of Gods mercy towards him in Chriſt.</hi> This is Mr. <hi>Dikes</hi> Judgment on <hi>Phil.</hi> 5. <hi>Firſt we muſt beleeve that Chriſt is ours, before we can be able to commit our ſelves to him, for the will and affections follow the underſtanding.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> in his N. Covenant, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf fully to be of this Judgment, and ſaith, <hi>Faith to receive Chriſt, is ever upon an abſolute Promiſe. pag.</hi> 56. which is as much as I affirm.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>The Promiſe propounded in the Goſpel, for the begetting of faith, is conditional, Beleeve, and be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is not the Goſpels firſt Promiſe. There is an abſolute indefinite Promiſe (I take an abſolute Promiſe for that, which ſhall certainly be accompliſhed in Gods Elect) precedent to this, viz. <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven is at hand,</hi> to which the command of Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the conditional Promiſe, hath relation. As in the Covenant of Works, firſt there is an abſolute Law given, and then a conditional Covenant made, <hi>Do this, and live:</hi> So in the Covenant of Grace, firſt there is made an abſolute Promiſe of Salvation through Chriſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179239:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>(taking abſolute in that ſenſe which I have named) and then a conditional Covenant, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, and be ſaved. When I am commanded to beleeve the Goſpel, or beleeve on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, it is intended, that I beleeve this abſolute Promiſe, not only Hiſtorically, but Applicatorily, and that I receive and relie upon Chriſt promiſed, and then I ſhall not periſh, but have everlaſting life. The act of faith is not terminated in the Promiſe, but in the ſimple term Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>There is no abſolute Promiſe of Salvation through Chriſt, in all the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is not ſo. The firſt Goſpel Promiſe of Grace and Life was abſolute, <hi>The ſeed of the Woman ſhall bruiſe the Serpents head,</hi> Gen. 3.15. This is renewed to <hi>Abraham, In thee ſhall all Families of the Earth be bleſſed,</hi> Gen. 12.3. Is not this a ſimple categorical Propoſition, and Declaration of Gods good will in Chriſt to the World? And this was Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel which was preached unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gal. 3.8. To make things more clear: Take an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Promiſe, for that which ſhall certainly be accompliſhed, and then the Goſpel alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins with an abſolute Promiſe both of end, and means, to wit, Salvation, and all means ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto, with relation to Gods Elect: of which kind are the Promiſes before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and 12.3. Let an abſolute Promiſe be taken for that which ſhall receive its accompliſhment, without any gracious precedent act of ours, and then the beginning of our Salvation, to wit, a new heart, a new ſpirit, and faith it ſelf, is abſolutely promiſed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.33, 34. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26, 27. If by Salvation be meant the continuance, perfecting, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of Salvation in Gods eternal, and everlaſting Kingdom, that is indeed promiſed upon condition, we put forth acts of faith, repentance, holineſs, and righteouſneſs throughout the whol courſe of our lives; all which conditions (as hath been ſaid) are abſolutely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. <hi>Conditiones N Faederis, non tantum praeceptae ſunt, ſed etiam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſae, Embd. Min.</hi> in the Synod of <hi>Dordt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Object. 3. <hi>The Promiſes to ſave abſolutely, and upon condition of beleeving, are inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To promiſe the beginning of Salvation abſolutely, and the continuance, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of Salvation, upon condition of an holy, penitential faith, ſtand well together. 2. To promiſe abſolutely, that is, aſſuredly, the continuance, perfecting, and conſummation of Salvation upon condition we actually beleeve, repent, and obey, is not inconſiſtent, becauſe the conditions are abſolutely promiſed.</p>
               <p>Object. 4. <hi>The abſolute Promiſe of Salvation through Chriſt, propounded in the Goſpel, is not particular, and perſonal, but general, and indefinite: and therefore if we beleeve it by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular application, we beleeve more than is revealed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though the abſolute Promiſe of Salvation through Chriſt, be general, and indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; yet is it made particular to every Elect Perſon, in his effectual call. This Promiſe is held forth with a commandment to apply it, and make it particular. So ſaith <hi>Zanchy, Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>De Naturâ Dei, Cap.</hi> 2. and Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> upon <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. When we are commanded to beleeve on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, this is one act that is required of us, to beleeve that Chriſt is ours, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.13. Whilſt this Goſpel is in preaching in our effectual Vocation, the Lord ſends the ſpirit of Adoption into our hearts, gives us a new heart, and a new ſpirit, which new ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit perſwades us to beleeve, and apply the Promiſe, and Chriſt promiſed, and it is all one as if he ſhould call us by name, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.1. <hi>John</hi> 10.3. They who are thus perſwaded by Chriſt, not only outwardly by his Word, but inwardly by his Spirit in their hearts, have a good ground to beleeve that the Promiſe belongs unto them, and that Chriſt is theirs, nor do they herein beleeve more than is revealed. To beleeve what Chriſt commands, is no Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſme.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:179239:12"/>
               <p>Object. 5. <hi>If all to whom the Goſpel is preached, are commanded to beleeve, that the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Promiſe belongs unto them, then are Reprobates commanded to beleeve a lye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. Zanchy</hi> upon <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.1. and Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Treatiſe of Predeſtination, anſwers thus in effect: <hi>Let Reprobates beleeve, and they ſhall not find it falſe, but true.</hi> But becauſe our act of Beleeving, works no change in the Object; and our beleeving, makes not a thing true, but it muſt be true before we beleeve, it is not ſatisfactory to me. Before I ſet down mine own apprehenſions (with humble ſubmiſſion to better Judgments) I think it requiſite that ſome things ſhould be premiſed: 1. I imbrace it for an undoubted truth, That <hi>falſum non eſt objectum fidei:</hi> The Spirit of Truth doth not perſwade men to beleeve Lyes. <hi>The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is truth, and is no lye,</hi> 1 John 2.27. <hi>2ly,</hi> All to whom the Goſpel cometh, are not only bound to put forth acts of Evangelical obedience, but to have the principles of theſe acts: for we loſt in <hi>Adam</hi> the very principles of yielding obedience to the holy Will of God, to wit, Integrity of Nature, with the preſence and aſſiſtance of Gods gracious Spirit. So that it is a ſin to be unregenerate, and to want the ſpirit of Grace, where the Goſpel is preached, <hi>Jude,</hi> 19. <hi>3ly,</hi> When Reprobates are commanded to beleeve, the Lord requires of them theſe two things, 1. That they have a new heart, and a new ſpirit, which is the ſpirit of Adoption, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31. <hi>2ly,</hi> That they Elicite an act of Faith, from this new heart excited by this new ſpirit. Let Reprobates then (according to the true ſence of the Goſpels Command) have a new heart, and a new ſpirit, and beleeve from theſe principles, that the abſolute promiſe of Grace belongs unto them, and they ſhall not beleeve a lye. Neither are Elect, nor Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates commanded actually to beleeve, immediately from the principles of Nature, but by the intervening of a new heart, and a new ſpirit, which are the principles of Grace: let theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervene, and then it is not required that they beleeve more than is revealed, and true. All true Chriſtians beleeve that this Promiſe belongs unto them, in habit, inclination, deſire, or act, of which there are many degrees.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="thesis">
               <head>
                  <hi>THESIS, IV.</hi> That all Promiſes proper and peculiar to the Goſpel, are abſolute.</head>
               <p>In the Covenant of Grace there are two ſorts of Promiſes: Some common to the Law with the Goſpel, though not for the matter, yet for the form into which they are put: as Beleeve and be ſaved, Repent and be ſaved, and theſe are conditional, belonging to Elect and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates. There be other Promiſes peculiar to the Goſpel both for matter and form; as <hi>a new heart will I give you, a new Spirit will I put within you,</hi> and theſe are abſolute, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. Which Promiſes though they be propounded in the promulgation of the Goſpel to all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, yet are they proper only to Gods Elect. Of theſe Promiſes is that to be underſtood which <hi>Proſper</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>De voc. Gent. Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Manet prorſus, et quotidiè impletur quod Abrahae Dominus ſine conditione promiſit, ſine lege donavit.</hi> And of theſe Promiſes doth <hi>Zanchy</hi> mean, <hi>Miſcell. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 13. where he ſaith, <hi>Promiſſiones de gratuitâ Dei miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiâ de<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> certa, et aeterna ſalute, etſi univer ſalitér omnibus proponuntur, et praedicandae ſunt: ad ipſos tamen tantum electos reipſa pertinent.</hi> And again, <hi>De Common. Divinis. Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um propriè quod annuntiat, id abſolutè citrà conditionem annuntiat.</hi> It was denyed in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod that there was any abſolute Promiſes. The Remonſtrants <hi>Collat. Hag. Band. pag.</hi> 190. <hi>lin.</hi> 22. aſſert, That the giving of a new heart is promiſed upon condition of our actual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. Others would have theſe Promiſes to be only Predictions and Propheſies, but ſeem to exclude them from being any part of the Covenant of Grace, whereas they be the chief, and proper part: or elſe I cannot ſee that our firſt Parents had any Goſpel preached unto them in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179239:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Paradice, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. There is nothing but an abſolute Promiſe expreſſed, (in which all abſolute Promiſes in both the ſences before mentioned are wrapt up) though I doubt not but the conditional Promiſe, Beleeve and be ſaved, is implied. Our Orthodox Divines in the Synod of <hi>Dordt,</hi> ſtand for theſe abſolute Promiſes as parts of the Covenant of Grace, againſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians, and that they are proper to the Goſpel in reſpect of their abſolute form, cannot be denied, the Law hath no Promiſes which run in that form. It is evident which <hi>Zanchy</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quicquid pertinet ad legem in ſcripturis, conditionale eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have loſt divers Notes by often removals, but (to my beſt remembrance) theſe, with one or two more of the like Nature, coincident with them, were all the Poſitions which at firſt I intended for Diſputation in the Synod. In heat of Diſcourſe in that Aſſembly, certain expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions fell from me, which were numbred amongſt my Errors, and made the chief matter of Diſpute by them who took all occaſions and advantages to make me ſeem erroneous. Amongſt the reſt (how it came in I do not well know) I ſaid, That Chriſt was part of the new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Queſtion is, What is meant by the new Creature, or new Man, which Chriſtians are commanded to put on? I anſwer, Partly Chriſt with his new created Righteouſneſs, partly new created qualities in us. Which (I conceive) may thus be proved: <hi>Adam</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and Chriſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Adam</hi> is the old man, and Chriſt the new man. Hereupon (tropically) all ſin which entred into the World by <hi>Adam,</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Old man; and all that righteouſneſs which is brought in by Chriſt, is called the New man; which righteouſneſs of Chriſts becomes ours in our New Birth, partly by Imputation, partly by Regeneration, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.15.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>By the Old man which we are to put off, is only meant Sin, not</hi> Adam<hi>'s Perſon: and therefore by the New man, is only meant new qualities in us, and not Chriſt's Perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the Old man may be underſtood, not only the corruption of Nature, which paſſeth from <hi>Adam</hi> to us, but his diſobedience, which becomes ours by imputation. So that in ſome reſpect we are to put off <hi>Adam,</hi> that is, the tranſgreſſion of <hi>Adam</hi> in eating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Fruit, which was his in act, and ours <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and originally. I am not the firſt who have taken the New man in that ſenſe, which if it be not proper, yet is it true. We are to put on Chriſt as well by Faith, as by imitation. I ſhall not much herein contend. <hi>Zanchy</hi> upon <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. having ſet down the judgment of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> what is meant by the New man which Chriſtians are to put on, (who underſtood it of Chriſt himſelf) and of others interpreting it of new qualities, delivers his own mind, and joyns them both together. <hi>Novus igitur ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo primum eſt Chriſtus ipſe in nobis inhabitans: deinde ipſe nova totius hominis qualitas, et natura per Chriſtum in nobis creata, poſtremo nos ipſi Chriſto induti, et novae illius naturae par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipes effecti, et in virtute (ut loquuntur ſcholia) viventes.</hi> Ye would likewiſe have wreſted other expreſſions which fell from me, to a corrupt ſence; as if I denied acting from a formal principle of Grace, or that any power was conveyed by the Commandments of the Law to act graciouſly, which was far from my ſence. The Opinion of <hi>Peter Lombart, Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 18. that Charity is not any thing created in the ſoul, but the Holy Ghoſt himſelf, is ſufficiently confuted by <hi>Aquinas,</hi> 22. c. q. 23.2. Far be it from me to deny the work of Regeneration or new qualities. This was my meaning in theſe paſſages; that we cannot act graciouſly from any inward principle of Grace, further than we are acted upon by the Spirit of Chriſt in Union. That the Commandments of the Law, are never accompanied by the Spirit, enabling us to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them, being ſevered from Chriſt, and the Covenant of Grace, or before faith come. Surely I maintained none of theſe Points in the Synod, which you make the Ground-work of Sedltion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, I am much condemned by you for obſtinacy after conviction. Of what was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179239:13"/>I convicted? Was it of laying the Magiſtrates, Elders, and the moſt part of the Country un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a covenant of works, abſolutely, and that to the knowledg of the hearers, out of Contempt of Authority to ſtir up Sedition? Contempt of Authority and ſedition is then made the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances &amp; principles of an act, to wit the laying them under a covenant of works in that ſort. If that act be not proved, contempt of Authority and Sedition vaniſh away, having no ſubject to which they do adhere. A man cannot be juſtly condemned for wilful murder unleſs it appear that he hath committed murder: nor can I be juſtly condemned for laying men under a covenant of works in that manner out of Contempt of Authority, to rayſe up ſedition, except it can be made evident, that I did lay them under that Covenant. That is then to be enquired into, &amp; proved by the Court that the Magiſtrates, Elders and moſt of the Country were the men whom I deſcribed and affirmed to be under a Covenant of works: otherwiſe contempt of Authority, &amp; ſedition falls to the ground having no foundation. The Court proceeded againſt me (as they ſaid Ex officio which in caſe of publick infamy, and manifeſt evidence of the fact, is not only lawful, but neceſſary) and when I humbly requeſted of the Honoured Court, that my accuſers might come forth, it was anſwered by them that my ſermon was my accuſer. Then muſt my Sermon accuſe me of that fact which they judged contemptuous, and Seditious, or elſe I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned without any accuſation or accuſers, meerly from their wil, and pleaſure. How wil they make it appeare that my Sermon was my accuſer? The Elders in their ſecret Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhewed them a way how to do it, viz. by forcing my Sermon to ſpeak thus; That faith, and repentance are no parts of the Goſpel. That Sanctification is no good evidence of a good eſtate. That they who ſee in themſelves any Sanctification, and thence conclude a good eſtate ſhal never be ſaved. That they who are not of this judgment, are Antichriſtians, enemys to Chriſt and under a covenant of works. This is made the ground by Mr. <hi>Weld</hi> in the ſhort ſtory but the Court did not declare themſelves to ſentence me upon this proofe. How then wil they make my ſermon my accuſer. I know not how except it was thus; To take a propoſition out of my ſermon. And an aſſumption which the Elders brought in (as hath been ſaid) and to conclude againſt me as though I had been author of them both, was the falſe accuſation, or application &amp;c. of my Sermon. Do you think in your Conſcience that this was conviction, and that I perſiſt obſtinate after conviction, my circumſtantial failing I have acknowledged. I did not much inquire after an Apology which I heard was written in the Courts defence, becauſe I know very wel that the cauſe was uncapable of any juſt defence. I knew that if al the men in the world ſhould combine together they could not make a bad cauſe good, no, not the Lord himſelf: the defect lieth not in God, but in the thing. Let a man twiſt ten thouſand ſins, together, he cannot cover ſin with ſin. If your cauſe was ſo juſt and convincing why have you deſerted the true cauſe, and ſet up a new title? prove the ground of the Courts ſentence out of my ſermon, or elſe you ſay nothing.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, You tel a ſtory of a man, whom (as you ſay) I led into theſe damnable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and hereſies.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the free promiſes are only for them under the Law.</item>
                  <item>2. That al our aſſurance is by immediate revelation.</item>
                  <item>3. That in the New Teſtament there are no ſignes.</item>
                  <item>4. That Baptiſme of water is of no uſe to them, who are Baptized by the holy Ghoſt.</item>
                  <item>5. That a man may be adopted, and not juſtified.</item>
                  <item>6. That every new creature is a dead lumpe, and acts not at al.</item>
                  <item>7. That we have no inherent righteouſneſs.</item>
                  <item>8. That the commandments are a dead letter.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I do reject, and abominate al theſe corrupt opinions as none of mine againſt which I do
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:179239:14"/>oppoſe theſe following poſitions as mine own judgment.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the free promiſes are no parts of the covenant of works, but of Grace.</item>
                  <item>2. That we do not only come to an aſſurance of a good eſtate by the immediate Teſtimony of the Holy-ghoſt, but alſo by that which is mediate, from faith, repentance, and works of ſanctification.</item>
                  <item>3. That in the New Teſtament the Lord gives to his confederates ſignes of their being in Covenant with him both inward, and outward.</item>
                  <item>4. That Chriſtians who are inwardly and inviſibly ingraffed into Chriſt, ſtand in need of an outward viſible baptizing into him, and into one body.</item>
                  <item>5. That juſtification, and adoption, are inſeparable benefits, flowing from our union with Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>6. That every new creature acts from an inward formal principle of Spiritual life.</item>
                  <item>7. That we are not only juſtified by the imputed righteouſneſs of Chriſt received by faith, but alſo have an inherent righteouſneſs infuſed into us by the ſpirit of regeneration.</item>
                  <item>8. The Commandements are the ſpirits inſtrument, to quicken Gods elect.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The authors of the ſhort ſtory, do not propound this to be credited barely upon their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, (for than they might have deluded the reader, who would beleeve it becauſe of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) but this witneſs which they beare againſt me in ſuch a matter of weight conſiſts of this hypothetical propoſition; If M. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> tenderly contradicted this poor man, being newly come to the profeſſion of religion, then muſt he needs learne thoſe points of Mr. <hi>Wheel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> or draw them as neceſſary conſequents from ſome of his Tenents</p>
               <p>The Conſequent part of this propoſition doth not follow from the Antecedent, here is no good conſequence. And therefore this their Teſtimony muſt needs appeare to be palpably falſe, to al ſuch as have the uſe of reaſon. How they ſhould conſcientiouſly ground ſuch an accuſation upon ſuch an argument I cannot apprehend.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fiftly You much glory in my conceived ruine, and cal your proceedings againſt me to baniſhment, the Lords marvellous doings. If by ruine you meane the ruine of my doctrine, and cauſe, there is no ſuch matter, that you have not touched: it is a doctrine and cauſe of your own deviſing, and ſetting up which you have ruined. If by ruine you underſtand ruine in reſpect of my outward man, I muſt needs ſay you have laboured to the utmoſt, to bring me to ruine, in my ſelf, Wife, Eleven children, Family, poſterity by ſuch acts before, in, and after my baniſhment, as I ſhal not now mention: (for I love not to complaine, I ſerve no hard maſter, the Lord is my ſheild and my exceeding great reward) yet even in this regard, hath not the Lord delivered me over unto the wil of my adverſaries, bleſſed be his name. If I and mine be ruinated by you temporally, and proſper ſpiritually, ye ſhal do us no great hurt by ſuch a ruine. What though ye thought evil againſt me? the Lord meant it unto good. But why do you cal your doings in exiling, and afflicting of me, the Lords marvellous doings The queſtion then is this; whether your proceedings againſt me be Gods work, or yours? This may eaſily be thus determined; If you can make it appear, that I am an Antinomian, Familiſt, Libertine. Seducer, guilty of Contempt of Authority, and Sedition, The Author of al theſe errors, and hereſies to which you relate me, in the ſhort ſtory that I am ſuch a flagiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heretick, evil man, and ſeducer, and vile miſcreant as you paint me forth to be, then may the proceedings be accounted Gods worke. If you cannot make this apparent, then is your proceedings againſt me, your own injurious, unrighteous, and more ſinful work, in which you live impenitent to this day, by a dangerous defect which lyeth in your wils, I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that this worke of which you ſo much boaſt, was the Lords marvellous decreed, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted work; but if you cannot make it evident, that it was the Lords marvellous comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179239:14"/>and approved doings, it makes nothing againſt me, nor for you. The Lord in mercy grant that this work which you have made with me, that you ſo highly extol, magnify, and put upon record amongſt Gods marvellous doings, be never layd to the charge of <hi>New England:</hi> If I ſhould anſwer to al the objections, and criminations made againſt me, by the ſhort ſtory, I ſhould to little purpoſe weary out my ſelf, and the reader. What I have thought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired any reply, to that I have anſwered, the reſt I paſs by in ſilence, committing my ſelf, and my cauſe, unto him who judgeth righteouſly.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Samuel Rutherford</hi> in his ſurvey of Antinomianiſme finding me deeply wounded and caſt out amougſt a company of Antinomians, Familiſts, Libertines, as their head, and leader, by the writer of the ſhort ſtory, falls upon me, ſmites me <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhoots many a deadly Arrow through the very heart of my good name. The paſſages which I take notice of in the ſurvey relating to me, are theſe following.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Except my heart deceive me, give me leave to borrow an expreſſion of <hi>Job,</hi> if I lift up my hand, or a bloody pen againſt the truly Godly, or have a pick at holyneſs, let my arme fal from my ſhoulder blade, and mine arme be broken from the bone, <hi>Job.</hi> 31.21.22. Epiſt. Page. 1.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It was obſerved in <hi>New England,</hi> when Familiſts grew, and in other parts of <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Familiſts deviſed ſuch a difference, between the Covenant of works, and of grace, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after a Sermon preached by Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> a prime familiſt. &amp;c. Page. 38. 39.</p>
               <p n="3">3 If Familiſts have ſuch revelations. 1. They ſee the viſions of God. 2. They ſpeak as acted by the ſpirit immediatly, and ſo we are by the ſame certainty of faith to beleeve what H. <hi>Nicholas. Wheelwright,</hi> &amp;c. Pag. 40.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Mr. <hi>Knop</hi> propheſied of the hanging of the Lord of <hi>Grange,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Daviſon</hi> uttered propheſies known to many of the Kingdom, divers holy, and mortified preachers in England, have done the like: No familiſts, or Antinomians, no <hi>David George,</hi> nor <hi>H. Nicholas</hi> no man of that Gang, <hi>Randal,</hi> or <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> or <hi>Den. &amp;c.</hi> Page. 42.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The firſt author of theſe wicked opinions, were, <hi>N. Wheelwright,</hi> ſome adherents to Mr. <hi>Wheelwright, &amp;c.</hi> Page. 176.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> and others were convened before a civil Court in <hi>Maſſachuſet. October.</hi> 2. 1637. For diſturbance of the publick peace, where in the Month of <hi>March</hi> Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> was convict of Sedition: upon occaſion whereof a number of Familiſts gave in a petition, or remonſtrance complaining that their beloved Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> was condemned for no fault, whereas his doctrine was no other then the very expreſſions of the Holy-Ghoſt himſelf, though he had ſaid expreſly that Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and moſt of the people were under a Covenant of works and therefore were enemies to Chriſt, ſuch as <hi>Herod, Pilate,</hi> Scribes, Pharaſees, and encouraged the people to riſe up againſt them, as Phyliſtins. &amp;c. Page. 177. 178. Part. 1.</p>
               <p>By what I have here tranſcribed out of the ſurvey it is evident, that Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> makes himſelf my judg. Severing me (in his notion) from the ſheep, and ſets me amonſt goats, condemning me amongſt the reſt, as a man not truely Godly. And that he ſo judgeth, he ſweares, oppignorating his Arme to the Shoulder blade.</p>
               <p>This is a dreadful ſentence which is paſſed againſt me, in reſpect of my perſonal ſtanding, by Mr. <hi>Rutherford.</hi> If he had thus judged me according to the Goſpel, I ſhould have trembled but becauſe it is done according to his own imagination, and eſpecially the ſhort ſtory, I deſpiſe it. Whether I truly feare God or no, is better known to me then Mr. <hi>Rutherford.</hi> I do not love to ſpeak of any great matters concerning my ſelf, the cheif of al ſinners: yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179239:15"/>I am called, and compelled thereunto. I ſhal a little glory in the Lord. After ſeven yeares ſpirit of bondage (as I remember,) for the ſpace of this five and twenty yeares, or there abouts, ever ſince the loving kindneſs of our Lord, and Saviour did appeare to the eye of my faith, juſtifying of me freely by his grace, I have (through Gods infinite mercy,) known in whom I do beleeve, and though I have been aſſaulted with innumerable temptations out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and inward in theſe perillous, deluding times: yet have I not (through mercy) put away a good Conſcience, or made ſhipwrack of my faith. Doubtleſs Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> is a very learned man, and I hope, a Godly man: yet is he but a man, and this judgment of his is meerly mans judgment, it proceeds not from God. With me it is a very ſmal thing to be judged of him, or of mans judgment; but he that judgeth me is the Lord. By the grace of God I am what I am.</p>
               <p>After that he hath thus judged my perſon, then he comes to condemne my doctrine, and practiſe. He cals me a Familiſt, a prime Familiſt, Author of thoſe wicked opinions, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the ſhort ſtory, a man convicted of Sedition, and what not? If I were ſuch a man as he deſcribes, he might wel judg me to be a man that doth not truly feare God, he might know me by my fruit. But this fruit is the fruit of my adverſaries vain imaginations, and (through Gods great goodneſs) did never grow on me. If I had been ſuch a man as you repreſent me to the world, the Lord himſelf would have Stigmatized me with a witneſs. If ſhould out of Gods judgment, grow worſe, and worſe deceiving and being deceived, my folly, and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would have been made manifeſt unto al men, I ſhould have been filthy, and unjuſt ſtil: the Lord who gave <hi>Jezabel</hi> a time to repent, and ſhe repented not, caſt her into a bed, killed her children with death, would diſcover my hereſy. and wickedneſs, (though I laboured never ſo cunningly to palliate the ſame, and al the Churches ſhould have known, that God is he who ſearcheth the Reines, and hearts. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.21.22.23. You have ſet upon me al the fearful works of reprobation. God takes them off by his word and acts of providence. Is not the witneſs of God alone more to be credited then the witneſs of you al? Indeed <hi>Mr. Rutherford</hi> glories much in one of his witneſſes, whom he ſuppoſeth to be the Author of the ſhort Story. Let it then be taken for granted that Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> is my lawful judg, yet he hath no witneſs, (ſo far as I know) but the Author of the ſhort ſtory, who is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, conceales his name againſt natures light, and hath born notable falſe witneſs againſt me in that he did accuſe me of ſeducing a man, and leading of him into many wicked errors, upon ſuch a weak ground as I have ſhewed: and his other witneſs is Mr. <hi>Thomas Weld,</hi> both of them being parties in the cauſe. Will he now condemne me upon this account before he heare what I can plead for my ſelf? Is this righteous judgment? Admit there be more witneſſes, and Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> ſtand up as an other witneſs (for ſo he is in this caſe) it is not the multitude nor Godlineſs of the witneſſes that makes their teſtimony true, but the conformity which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the teſtimony, and the thing teſtifyed. Is Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> certain that what he reports is true? He knows very wel, that <hi>mendacio annumeratur aſſeveratio rei incertae pro certa, quamvis putamus eſſe veram.</hi> Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> ſtands as it were upon the ſhoulders of the ſhort Story-writers, takes his bloody pen (as he cals it) into his hand, draws blood of many ſound men in judgment, the deare Saints, and ſervants of God, whoſe blood in the ſight of God is precious, and what they report he reports, and more too, with much paſſion, and in moſt reproachful language, where I leave him to ſtand or fal with them.</p>
               <p>To conclude, this is the ſum of my anſwer to Mr. <hi>Thomas Weld</hi> and Mr. <hi>S. Rutherford;</hi> The true real cauſe of my ſufferings, in my Eſtate, Liberty, Name, Miniſtry: in my Self, Wife, Children, Family, under the name of hereſy, contempt of Authority, and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was that doctrine contained in my firſt three propoſitions, wherein I differed from ſome
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179239:15"/>of my brethren about the grounds of a ſpecial faith, and the order of evidencing a good eſtate, It was of late attempted to bring me under new ſufferings for delivering the ſame doctrine in a Sermon which I preached at <hi>Boſton</hi> at the Court of Election, and it was objected, that I raked up the old matter. This true cauſe is ſilenced by them both.</p>
               <p>Certain of my brethren the Elders deviſed a cauſe againſt me (as I have ſhewed and can prove) differing from this in ſubſtance which they preſented to the Court, yet never brought it to publick view, but makes uſe of it amongſt themſelves, prejudicing the Court and their freinds againſt me. This falſe fained cauſe is publiſhed by the ſhort Story writers and Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> follows them. I commit the further clearing up of theſe things unto the Lord, who wil bring every work to judgment with every ſecret thing whether it be good, or whether it be evil. To God only wiſe be prayſe through Jeſus Chriſt for ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. What credit is to be given to the wittneſs borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me by Mr. <hi>Weld,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> wil more evidently appeare by theſe oppoſite Teſtimonies which I do here annex.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> in his anſwer to Mr. <hi>Baly</hi> Pag. <hi>60. 61.</hi> Makes this report; Neither the Church nor my ſelfe did ever look at Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> either as an Antinomian or Familiſt Many of us knew that he had taken good pains againſt both, and in that very place where he was wont to preach; inſomuch that one of his hearers (who ſince joyned to Mr. <hi>Gortons</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety) openly conteſted againſt his doctrine as falſe, and Antichriſtian. And when Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> was put out of this Country (though he be ſince reſtored) ye if he had cleaved to the errors the companys fel into, he would never have refuſed their earneſt invitation, and cal of him, to Miniſter unto them. They ſent to him, and urged him much to come to them to a far richer ſoyl, and richer company then where he lived: yet he conſtantly refuſed, and upon that very ground becauſe of the Corruption of their judgments: Profeſſing often while they pleaded for the Covenant of grace, they tooke away the grace of the Covenant.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <head>To The Honoured general Court now aſſembled at <hi>Boſton,</hi> the Petition of the Church, and Town of <hi>Hampton.</hi> 26. 2. 1654.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Humbly Sheweth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THat whereas our Reverend Paſtor M. <hi>John Wheelwright</hi> doth deeply Suffer in his name, as an heretical, criminous perſon, eſpecially by two printed books: the one written by <hi>Mr. Thomas Weld,</hi> the other by Mr. <hi>Samuel Rutherford,</hi> Which hath and wil have a ſad influence upon his perſon, Miniſtry, Family, Wife, Children, and poſterity for ever; and they ſeem to us cheifly to ground their charge upon this Honoured Courts proceedings againſt him, who cenſured him to Baniſhment for Contempt of Authority, and ſedition: and condemned him in a Court order for ſeducing many of the people of <hi>New-England</hi> into dangerous errors, by his opinions, and Revelations, So that it was feared, that they would make ſome ſudden irrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them of contrary judgment as they did in <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our humble requeſt therefore unto this Honored Court is, that they would be pleaſed to take into their conſideration their ſeveral acts concerning him and if it appeare that he ſuffered fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:179239:16"/>then cauſe required through any miſtake, that ſome courſe might be taken for the healing and reparation of his name. Otherwiſe (we do conceive) that we are not long like to enjoy his miniſtry, and preſence amongſt us: whom (to our beſt diſcerning) we have ever found, orthodox, and ſound in judgment, upright and blameleſs in life, and converſation. Whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from us wil tend to our great detriment both to our inward, and outward man, if not deſtructive to our peace, and welfare. We leave our requeſt in the hands of your worſhips, for whoſe good guidance, by Gods gracious preſence we pray.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="court_order">
            <head>At a general Court held at <hi>Boſton,</hi> 24. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1654.</head>
            <p>THis Court taking into conſideration the good ſervice, and great uſe which Mr. <hi>John Wheelwright</hi> hath been, and is of in the Towns of <hi>Hampton,</hi> and adjacent places and the earneſt endeavours which that Town hath uſed for his continuance there amongſt them, and hearing that on ſome acts which have paſſed from this Court, that Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> is by Mr. <hi>Rutherford,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Weld</hi> rendred in ſome books printed by them as heretical and crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inous; Now that they the ſaid Mr. <hi>Rutherford,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Weld</hi> nor any other by their means may be led into miſapprehenſions of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> we do ſignify that Mr. <hi>Wheel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> hath for theſe many yeares approved himſelf a ſound, orthodoxe, and profitable Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel amongſt theſe churches of Chriſt of which he now ſtandeth a Paſtor in one of them. This is a true copie taken out of the Courts Records.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edward Rawſon. Secret.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_notice">
            <p>The Church and Town of Hampton teſtify that they have ever judged me Orthodoxe, and The Honoured Court for many years. Though the Court ſeem to limit their approving Teſtimony to certain yeares: yet am I perſwaded that they are ſo Godly, and Conſcientious, that they wil not ſay that I formerly held theſe corrupt opinions charged upon me by the ſhort ſtory which I have ſince revoked. That from the beginning of my troubles they were fathered upon me, without any juſt cauſe, my conſcience beares me wittneſs and God is my wittneſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>The Names of Books printed by <hi>Peter Cole,</hi> Printer and Book-ſeller of <hi>London:</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the ſign of the Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-preſs in Cornhil, neer the Royal Exchange.</head>
            <head type="sub">Mr. <hi>Hookers</hi> New Books in three Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lums: One in Octavo, and two in Quarto.</head>
            <p>Theſe Eleven New Books of Mr. <hi>Thomas Hooker,</hi> made in <hi>New-England</hi> Are atteſted in an Epiſtle by Mr. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Goodwin,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Philip Nye,</hi> To be written with the Authors Own hand: None being written by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before. One Volum being a Comment upon Chriſt's laſt Prayer in the Seventeenth of <hi>John:</hi> wherein is opened, The <hi>Union</hi> beleevers have with God and Chriſt, and the glorious Priviledges thereof. Beſides many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goſpel Truths, there is alſo ſhewed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179239:16"/>
            <list>
               <head>Twenty one ſeveral Books of Mr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Bridge,</hi> Collected into two Volumns. <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>1 Scripture Light the moſt ſure Light.</item>
               <item>2 Chriſt in Travel:</item>
               <item>3 A Lifting up for the Caſt down,</item>
               <item>4 Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</item>
               <item>5 Sins of Infirmitie.</item>
               <item>6 The falſe Apoſtle tried and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered</item>
               <item>7 The good and means of Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</item>
               <item>8 The great things Faith can do.</item>
               <item>9 The great things Faith can ſuffer.</item>
               <item>10 The Great Goſpel Myſtery of the Saints Comfort and Holineſs, opened and applied from Chriſts Prieſtly Office.</item>
               <item>11 Satans power to Tempt, and Chriſts Love to, and Care of his People under Temptation</item>
               <item>12 Thankfulneſs required in every Condition.</item>
               <item>13 Grace for Grace.</item>
               <item>14 The Spiritual Actings of Faith through Natural Impoſſibilities.</item>
               <item>15 Evangelical Repentance</item>
               <item>16 The Spiritual Life, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>17 The Woman of Canaan.</item>
               <item>18 The Saints Hiding-place, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>19 Chriſts Coming &amp;c.</item>
               <item>20 A Vindication of Goſpel Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</item>
               <item>21 Grace and Love beyond Gifts</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Twelve Books of Mr. <hi>Jeremiah Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> lately publiſhed;</head>
               <item>1 Goſpel Reconciliation, Or Chriſts Trumpet of Peace to the World. Wherein is Opened Gods exceeding willingneſs to be Reconciled to Man; And Gods ſending his Embaſſadors to that End. From. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19, 20, 2</item>
               <item>2 The Rare Jewel of Chriſtian Contentment.</item>
               <item>3 Goſpel-worſhip.</item>
               <item>4 Goſpel-Converſation,</item>
               <item>5 A Treatiſe of Earthly-minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. A Treatiſe of Heavenly-mindedneſs, and walking with God.</item>
               <item>6 An <hi>Expoſition</hi> on the fourth, fifth, ſixth, and ſeventh Chapters of the Propheſie of <hi>Hoſea.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 An <hi>Expoſition</hi> on the eighth, ninth, and tenth Chapters of <hi>Hoſea.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 An <hi>Expoſition</hi> on the eleventh, twelfth, and thirteenth Chapters of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> being now compleat.</item>
               <item>9 The <hi>Evil of Evils,</hi> or the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſinfulneſs of ſin, on <hi>Job</hi> 16.21.</item>
               <item>10 Precious Faith, on 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1.</item>
               <item>11 Of Hope, on 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.3.</item>
               <item>12 Of Walking by Faith, on 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> his fifty nine Sermons on <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28, 29, 30. Are Printing</p>
            <p>A Godly and Frut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Expoſition,</hi> on the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Peter.</hi> By Mr. <hi>John Rogers,</hi> Miniſter of the word of God at <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Rogers</hi> on <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian, his Diſeaſe and Cure: Diſcovering the Leproſie of Sin and Self-love; with the Cure, <hi>viz.</hi> Self-denial and Faith.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> his Treatiſe of Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</p>
            <p>The Wonders of the Loadſtone. By <hi>Samuel ward</hi> of <hi>Ipſwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An <hi>Expoſition</hi> on the Goſpel of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt
<pb facs="tcp:179239:17"/>St. <hi>Matthew.</hi> By Mr. <hi>VVard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Diſcipline of the Church in <hi>New-England:</hi> By the Churches and Synod there.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Phyſick Books of <hi>Nich. Culpeper,</hi> Gent. Student in Phyſick and Aſtrologie, formerly publiſhed.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>The Idea of Practical Phyſick. in twelve books,</hi> Viz.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 The art to preſerve Health.</item>
                     <item>2 Of The preternatural diſorder of mans body, and their Signs.</item>
                     <item>3 Of Medicaments.</item>
                     <item>4 Of the art of Healing.</item>
                     <item>5 Of the general Cure of Diſeaſes.</item>
                     <item>6 Of External Diſeaſes.</item>
                     <item>7 Of Feavers.</item>
                     <item>8 Of Head Diſeaſes.</item>
                     <item>9 Of middle Belly Diſeaſes.</item>
                     <item>10 Of Lower belly Diſeaſes.</item>
                     <item>11 Of Venemous Diſeaſes.</item>
                     <item>12 Of Childrens Diſeaſes.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Written By <hi>John Johnſtone,</hi> Doctor of Phyſick:</head>
               <item>1 The Practice of Phyſick.</item>
               <item>2 A Sure Guide to Phyſick and Chyurgery: That is to ſay, The Arts of Healing by Medicine, and Manual Operation. Being an Anatomical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the whole body of Man, In Six Books. And adorned with a hundred eighty four Figures cut in Braſs.</item>
               <item>3 Veſlingius Anatomy of the Body of Man.</item>
               <item>4 A Tranſlation of the New di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſatory, made by the Colledg of Phyſitians of London.</item>
               <item>5. The Engliſh Phyſitian enlarged.</item>
               <item>6 A Directory for Midwives.</item>
               <item>7 Galens Art of Phyſick.</item>
               <item>8 A New Method both of ſtudying and practiſing Phyſick.</item>
               <item>9 A Treatiſe of the Rickets,</item>
               <item>10 Medicaments for the Poor, Or Phyſick for the Common People.</item>
               <item>11 Health for the Rich and Poor, by Dyet without Phyſick.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>London Diſpenſatory</hi> in Folio, of a large Character in Latine.</p>
            <p>The <hi>London Diſpenſatory</hi> in twelves, a ſmal Pocket Book in Latine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:179239:17"/>
            <p>THere be ſundry Faults eſcaped in the printing (without any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table change of the ſence) which the Reader is intreated to correct.</p>
            <p>That part of the Title, <hi>Free Grace maintained againſt Mr.</hi> Weld, <hi>late of</hi> New-England, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Rutherford, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is none of the Authors.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:179239:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179239:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
